<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Abra-Mulè, or, A true history of the dethronement of Mahomet IV written in French by M. Le Noble ; made English by J.P.</title>
            <title>Abra-Mulè. English</title>
            <author>Le Noble, Eustache, 1643-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47670</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12935543</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12935543</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47670)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 388:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Abra-Mulè, or, A true history of the dethronement of Mahomet IV written in French by M. Le Noble ; made English by J.P.</title>
                  <title>Abra-Mulè. English</title>
                  <author>Le Noble, Eustache, 1643-1711.</author>
                  <author>J. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Abra-Mulè, ou, L'histoire de la deposition de Mahomet IV.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mehmed --  IV, --  Sultan of the Turks, 1642-1693 --  Fiction.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra-Mulè</hi> OR, A TRUE HISTORY Of the Dethronement of <hi>MAHOMET</hi> IV.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in</hi> French <hi>by</hi> M. Le Noble.</p>
            <p>Made <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>J. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Clavel</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> near St. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To his moſt Serene Highneſs, Monſeigneur the Prince of <hi>CONTI.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Monſeigneur,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Unfortunate <hi>Abra-Mulè,</hi> belov'd by two Sultan's and a Viſir, yet ſo, that neither of the three could be happy in the enjoyment of her, is come into <hi>France,</hi> to unfold the ſecret In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treagues which her Beauty occaſion'd in the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio,</hi> and which pull'd down <hi>Mahomet</hi> from the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Throne.</p>
            <p>She begs to appear under the Auſpices of your Serene Highneſs, and ſhe is in hopes, Sir, that a Prince, who together with all the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of a perfect Hero, poſſeſſes all that Love is capable to inſpire, will not refuſe a Sultaneſs ſo amiable and ſo vertuous, the honour of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. She flatters her ſelf with it, Sir, and the troubles that overwhelm her will meet with a pleaſing Conſolation, if your ſerene Highneſs, while you recreate your weary'd Thoughts in reading the fatal Succeſs of a Tenderneſs ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal as hers, afford it ſome little ſence of your Compaſſion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:3"/>
            <p>But, Sir, Your ſerene Highneſs will not only behold in this ſhort Hiſtory the ſecret of an amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Intreague, you will ſee there the Events of War, which will be yet more pleaſing to that undaunted Courage which renders you the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your Country. This undaunted Courage, ſupported by all that can form an accompliſh'd <hi>Hero,</hi> is the fire of that Royal Blood that runs in your Veins; an Emanation of the great Soul of that invincible Prince, that incomparable <hi>Condè,</hi> whom <hi>France</hi> beholds with ſo much pleaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd in your vertues.</p>
            <p>Continue, Sir, continue to tread the ſteps of that Gyant, and may that formidable arm of yours, the weight of which the Enemies of the State ſo often have felt, be one of the moſt firm ſupports of the firſt Monarchy in the World. My good Wiſhes follow you where ever you go, and the chiefeſt wiſh I make at preſent, while I take the liberty to offer you this little Piece, is, that ſo long as I live, I may be,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſes moſt Humble and moſt Obedient, <hi>LE NOBLE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>'TIS not to be imagin'd that this is a Romantick Adventure grounded upon meer Invention; for it is the real Truth of a ſecret Intreague carry'd on in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> which put <hi>Soliman</hi> upon attempting to ſet himſelf up in the room of his Brother, meerly to gratifie an amorous Paſſion which render'd him his Rival.</p>
            <p>I have writ nothing but what I had from the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs of one of my intimate Friends, who accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying <hi>M. Gerardin</hi> in his Embaſſy, and abiding with him a long time at the Port under <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Reign, unravell'd there the whole Secret of this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, concerning which upon his Return, he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd all the Informations into my hands, at the ſame time that upon what I had div'd into by the Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondencies which I held in ſeveral parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> I publiſh'd thoſe Dialogues which include an infinite number of Particulars, not to be met with in other Hiſtorians.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:4"/>
            <p>This is therefore no chemerical Invention, but a true History; and if you take the pains to compare it with thoſe that are more General, you will find that I am very exact in all the Circumstances of Publick Events, and that I do but unfold the ſecret Reaſons that caus'd 'em</p>
            <p>The Actions of Soveraigns are always divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two parts; the one is the Publick Event, which all the World knows, and which is the Subject of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zettes, and the most part of publick Histories; the other is that which they conceal under the Vail of their Politicks; and thoſe are the ſecret Motives of the Intreagues which cauſe thoſe Events, and which are only known to, and reveal'd by thoſe, who had ſome ſhare in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on thoſe Intreagues, or who by the penetration of their Genius, knowing one part, divine the t' other.</p>
            <p>For Example, we read every where of the taking of <hi>Buda</hi> by the Valour of Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> ſeconded by the Duke of <hi>Bavaria;</hi> that they carry'd the Place in view of an Army of Fourſcore Thouſand Men, Commanded by the Viſir in perſon, who could not relieve it; but the Relations never tell yee, that the Conſpiracy carry'd on by Prince <hi>Soliman, Siaous</hi> and <hi>Cuproli,</hi> who were plotting the Ruin of the Viſir, hinder'd the Succours, and ty'd that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Arm.</p>
            <p>In like manner we find in the Publick Hiſtory of <hi>Philip II.</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that he was two Years in <hi>Flanders,</hi> without ever returning into <hi>England</hi> to viſit Queen <hi>Mary</hi> his Wife, not ſo much as during her mortal ſickneſs, but we do not ſee what motives of Love and Jealouſy ſet 'em at variance.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:4"/>
            <p>Thus it may be ſaid, that ſeeing Action is the Body, and that the motive is the ſoul of that Action, there are very few or no Historians, but what give us Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies without Souls, while they never tell us the Motives which cauſe Princes to Act, and give Motion to their Intreagues.</p>
            <p>Which is the Reaſon that particular Hiſtories are always more pleaſing, and more profitable then thoſe which are General: They are more pleaſing, becauſe there is more care taken to adorn 'em, and for that they mention thoſe things which are not to be met with in others: And they are more profitable, becauſe they are more preciſe in the Characters of Princes, and in the Private and Domeſtick Actions, which are more proper to inſtruct, then the general Relation of an Action, of which we know not the Motive nor the Cauſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="glossary">
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:5"/>
            <head>An Explication of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Terms contain'd in this Hiſtory.</head>
            <list>
               <label>SUltan.</label>
               <item>The Emperor of the <hi>Turks.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Sultaneſs Validè.</label>
               <item>The Sultaneſs, Mother of the Sultan.</item>
               <label>Sultaneſs Aſſeki.</label>
               <item>The principal favourite Sultaneſs.</item>
               <label>Grand Viſir.</label>
               <item>Chief Miniſter of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire.</item>
               <label>Mufti.</label>
               <item>Chief Prieſt.</item>
               <label>Iman.</label>
               <item>A Doctor, or Preacher of the <hi>Alcoran.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Dervis.</label>
               <item>A <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Monk.</item>
               <label>Alcoran.</label>
               <item>The Mahometan's Bible.</item>
               <label>Moſquee.</label>
               <item>A Mahometan Temple.</item>
               <label>Seraskier.</label>
               <item>A General of an Army.</item>
               <label>Baſha.</label>
               <item>A Governor.</item>
               <label>Kaimakan.</label>
               <item>High Marſhall of the Houſhold, and Governour of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Janiſaries.</label>
               <item>The <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Infantry, the Sultan's Guards.</item>
               <label>Aga.</label>
               <item>Collonel of the Janiſaries.</item>
               <label>Serraglio.</label>
               <item>The Sultan's Palace.</item>
               <label>Kiaia.</label>
               <item>A Lieutenant.</item>
               <label>Kiſler Agaſi.</label>
               <item>Chief of the black Eunuchs, and ſuperintendent of the <hi>Serraglio.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Kiſler Kiaſi.</label>
               <item>Deputy to the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Grand Teftardar.</label>
               <item>Lord Treaſurer.</item>
               <label>Boſtangi Bachi.</label>
               <item>Superintendent of the Sultan's Palaces, Gardens and Buildings, or chief Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyor.</item>
               <label>Boſtangi.</label>
               <item>A Gardner.</item>
               <label>Dragoman.</label>
               <item>An Interpreter.</item>
               <label>Catacheriff.</label>
               <item>A Decree of the Sultan.</item>
               <label>Fetfa.</label>
               <item>A decree of the <hi>Mufti.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Timar.</label>
               <item>A Feofment for Life.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95750:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Abra-Mulè:</hi> OR, THE HISTORY Of the Depoſition of <hi>MAHOMET</hi> IV. EMPEROR of the TURKS.</head>
            <head>The Firſt Part.</head>
            <p>THE Revolution which happen'd in the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, in the Month of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> by the Depoſal of Sultan <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> and the Advancement of <hi>Soliman</hi> his Brother to the Throne, is one of the greateſt Changes that have fallen out in this Age; and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95750:6"/>of which the ſecret Circumſtances that caus'd it, not div'd into by many Perſons, are moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be known.</p>
            <p>The greateſt part have attributed 'em only to the misfortunes of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Arms, and to this Principle of the <hi>Muſſelmen's</hi> belief, that when Adverſity attends a Man, 'tis an infallible ſign of the Wrath of God, and of the contempt of their Prophet, and conſequently that it is lawful to Sacrifice to the Publick Good the Prince whom they believe to be the ſubject of that Coeleſtial Anger.</p>
            <p>But though it muſt not be deni'd, but that the unlucky Conjunctures contributed very much to the Depoſal of the <hi>Sultan,</hi> by reaſon of the pretences with which they were ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd; nevertheleſs, the Truth is, that Love was the ſecret cauſe, and that that ſame Love only made uſe of a pretence which had its riſe from thence.</p>
            <p>However, before we enter into the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of this ſame extraordinary Story, it will be neceſſary for the better underſtanding of it, to give the Publick a general Idea of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family at that time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> a Prince cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el even to Barbariſm, was Strangl'd upon a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of his Janizaries, and Dying, left three Sons; <hi>Mahomet,</hi> between Nine and Ten Years of Age, who ſucceeded him under the Regency of the Sultaneſs his Mother; <hi>Soliman,</hi> about a year Younger, and <hi>Achmet,</hi> who was not then
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95750:6"/>above Four or Five Years Old, all three Born of different Sultaneſſes.</p>
            <p>Some there are who have aſſerted, that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> was not an <hi>Ottaman:</hi> That the Sultaneſs only fain'd her ſelf with Child, that ſhe might procure to her ſelf the Title of <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> or Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Mother of the Firſt-born Prince: That he was the Child of a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Woman that was brought to Bed in a Chamber near the Sultaneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe's; that the Infant was carry'd to her in a Bas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of Flowers, and afterwards ſet up and own'd by Her for a Child born of her own Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. The Author of the <hi>Ottoman Mirror</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhes this Story. But it is neither credible, nor to be imagin'd, that a project of this Nature ſhould be put in practice within the <hi>Serraglio;</hi> and if there had been the leaſt Suſpition for a ground of this Fable, <hi>Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>man,</hi> who dethron'd him, would never have ſpar'd his life, nor the life of the Prince his Son, who at this day wears the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Diadem.</p>
            <p>That which might have been the occaſion of this Fiction, might be this perhaps; that the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſs never had any other Children; that ſhe was at continual Odds with <hi>Mahomet,</hi> when he raign'd by himſelf; and for that ſhe Protected the other two Princes againſt the Violences of her Son, every time that he went about to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt their lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet,</hi> for Stature, was ſomewhat Taller then the ordinary Height, well Proportion'd, black Hair, little Eyes, but Quick, more ill Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95750:7"/>then Comely; nimble in all the Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Body, Valiant, Courtly, Profuſe, Magnificent, paſſionate in his Amours, a lover of Hunting even to Exceſs; an extraordinary diſcerner of Merit; but Raſh, Obſtinate, Ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and one that ſuffer'd himſelf to be very much govern'd by the Miniſters of the <hi>Serraglio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> was very Tall, Straight, Majeſtick, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to Fat, a pleaſing Countenance, large and black Eyes, with a lively and fair Complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; his Noſe and Mouth admirably Shap'd, the turn of his Countenance ſomewhat Oval, his Hands white and Fleſhy. He was Nimble at all Exerciſes that requir'd no great labour; he was naturally Melancholly, and full of Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; he ſpoke little; and whether it were out of Policy, or by Inclination, he devoted himſelf to the ſtudy of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> which he unfolded like a Doctor. He was Generous, Crafty and Bold, with a Heart moſt tenderly enclining to Love; but he was one who had an admirable Gift at concealing a ſecret.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Achmet,</hi> in regard he has no ſhare in this Hiſtory, 'tis needleſs to ſay any thing of him, only that Nature had deform'd his Body, and that he retain'd ſomething of his Fathers Stupidity, but nothing of his Cruelty.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Janizaries</hi> in the fury of their Sedition, ſet <hi>Mahomet</hi> upon the Throne, and engag'd him to give Order for putting his Father to Death. And for the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> his Mother, ſhe was one of the moſt beautiful Women in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95750:7"/>World; a <hi>Circaſſion,</hi> but of mean Birth, and one who from a Slave had mounted to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of Female Glory, by means of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius moſt ſublime, and capable of governing a great Empire.</p>
            <p>To fix her ſelf in her Authority, ſhe thought it behov'd her to advance to the Dignity of Grand Viſir, ſuch a perſon as ſhould be behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her for his Fortune and Preferment; and knowing the Capacity, the Courage, and the Wit of <hi>Baſha Cuproli,</hi> who then lay loaden with Irons at the bottom of a Dungeon, ſhe obtain'd his Releaſe, confer'd with him in Private, drew from him what Proteſtations and Aſſurances ſhe pleas'd her ſelf, and at the ſame time deliver'd to him the Seal of the Empire, and ſet him at the head of the Council, and the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>His Government was Proſperous and Prudent, his Fidelity inviolable, his Services advantageous; and laden with Honours and Victories, by a ſtrange fortune without example in the <hi>Ottoman.</hi> Empire; he had two Sons, and two Sons in Law, that ſucceeded him in his Employment.</p>
            <p>His Father was a <hi>French</hi> Renegado, born in <hi>Champagne,</hi> near <hi>Chalons,</hi> in a Village call'd <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perli,</hi> from whence he took his Name, being a Serjeant in a Foot Company, and which he left to his Poſterity. A certain Murder which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, enforc'd him to fly his Country, and the Bark to which he betook himſelf being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Corſairs, he thought it more convenient to wear a Turbant, then to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95750:8"/>chain'd to the Oar; and being a handſom perſon, he was ſoon enroll'd among the <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> among whom, having rais'd himſelf by his Valour to ſignal Employments, he obtain'd a <hi>Timar,</hi> or a proportion of Lands for Life, and ſpun ſo fair a Thread for himſelf, that by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees he arriv'd to the higheſt place of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. This is the truth, both of the Original and Name of the <hi>Cuproli</hi>'s, and whatever is aver'd to the contrary is meer Fiction.</p>
            <p>The cruel Polities of the <hi>Ottomans</hi> was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that formerly the <hi>Sultans</hi> always ſacrific'd the Blood of their Brothers to the ſecurity of their Government. But, the firſt Counſel which <hi>Cuproli</hi> gave the Sultaneſs <hi>Validè,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Mother,</hi> was carefully to preſerve the two Princes, <hi>Soliman</hi> and <hi>Achmet,</hi> not only to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Extinction of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Blood, but out of a ſecret Aim which the Viſir had to make a Bulwark for his own ſafety, both of the one and the other, and to have in his hands where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with all to keep his Maſter in continual aw, in caſe that when he came to Rule by himſelf, he might be induc'd by ſome intreague of the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio,</hi> to deprive him of the chief Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>Thus it came to paſs, that thoſe two Princes were beholding to <hi>Cuproli</hi> for their lives, who by a marvellous Dexterity of Wit, being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to mannage at a diſtance the ſeveral Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours both of <hi>Mahomet</hi> and <hi>Soliman,</hi> ſo order'd it, that his Eldeſt Son, who was about the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>'s Age, was bred in his Company among the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95750:8"/>Children of Honour, and that the Youngeſt was nurtur'd in company with <hi>Soliman.</hi> I relate this particular circumſtance, becauſe it will prove ſerviceable to unfold the intregue of this Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution carri'd on by this Young <hi>Cuproli.</hi> And indeed <hi>Soliman</hi> from his Infancy contracted ſo ſtrickt a Friendſhip with him, and with <hi>Siaous,</hi> who was next him in the ſame Quality, that thoſe two Perſons were his moſt ſecret Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. But in regard that as well by Nature, as by the care that was taken to inſtruct him, he was become a Maſter in Diſſimulation; this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence was ſo well manag'd, that it never gave <hi>Mahomet</hi> any cauſe of Suſpition.</p>
            <p>After this general <hi>Idea,</hi> we are now to enter into the ſecret of the Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>The great <hi>Cuproli</hi> being dead in the midſt of his Tryumphs, had for his Succeſſor his Eldeſt Son, who was bred up with <hi>Mahomet,</hi> but he dyed within a ſhort time after his Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>At that time the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire enjoy'd a perfect Tranquillity, by vertue of a Truce that was ſign'd by the Chriſtian Princes. <hi>Mahomet</hi> alſo, by the Sultaneſs <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> had a Son, a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Young Gentleman, and of promiſing Hopes, about twenty Years of Age, and he quietly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd the Fruit of his Victories which had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd him <hi>Candie, Kaminiec,</hi> and ſome places in <hi>Hungary;</hi> ſo that he abandon'd himſelf to the ſports of Hunting, and the pleaſures of Love, notwithſtanding the raging jealouſie of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95750:9"/>Sultaneſs, who oft-times broke his meaſures.</p>
            <p>But becauſe it is the temper of ſome Men, that they cannot contain themſelves when they are well, <hi>Kara Muſtapha,</hi> whom he had made choice of for his Grand Viſier, conſtrain'd him indiſcretly to break his Truce with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and plung'd him into a War no leſs fatal to him then unjuſt.</p>
            <p>The Truce was broken, <hi>Vienna</hi> Beſieg'd; but at the ſame time that the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Puiſſance ſeem'd ready to overturn the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Empire, the God of Battel, who diſtributes Victory according to the decrees of his Providence, ſtrook the Viſir with a Spirit of Terror and Confuſion; the Seige was rais'd by the aſſiſtance of the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Valour and Conduct of <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſignaliz'd all the following Campaigns with new Conqueſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet,</hi> during his Misfortunes, remitted nothing of his ſports; he had ſeveral Favourites, among the reſt whom he honour'd in a more particular manner, there was one <hi>Baſha,</hi> who was call'd by the Name of <hi>Soliman,</hi> and whom he had made <hi>Seraſquiſs,</hi> or General of his Arms, upon the Borders of <hi>Poland.</hi> He was about Thirty Years of Age, and it was a hard matter to meet with a more Graceful Perſon. He was a Man who had never a whit the leſs Valour for having been bred up in the ſoft pleaſures of the Court. He was Tall, and his Beauty which was Maſculine, and full of Fire, was ſeconded with a ſparkling Wit, which no way leſſen'd his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95750:9"/>his undauntedneſs was proof againſt all Danger, and his Addreſs imcomparable, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the Intreagues of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> wherein he had for his principal and inviolable Friend, the <hi>Kiſſer Agaſi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Officer is an Officer of the greateſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and power in the <hi>Serraglio:</hi> He is a black Eunuch, and is the chief of all the Eunuchs: To him belongs the ſuperintendancy over all the Sultaneſſe's Guards: Whatever concerns 'em de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon his abſolute Power; and it is a hard matter for a Woman to obtain or preſerve the favour of the Sultans, but by the intregues of this Eunuch. He ruins, or becomes ſerviceable to thoſe whom he has a mind to Favour, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy. And from thence 'tis an eaſie thing to conceive what immenſe. Riches he heaps up by means of the Preſents which he receives from the Sultaneſſes, who are ſenſible of his Kindneſs, or fear the Effects of his Ill-will; or from thoſe, who by the aſſiſtance of his Credit aſpire to great Employments. Laſtly, his place is ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he has Six Hundred Horſes kept for his ſervice only at the charges of the State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> undertook the Command of the Arms upon the Frontiers of <hi>Poland,</hi> at the beginning of the Campaign that was ſignaliz'd by the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel of <hi>Gran.</hi> At what time one of the principal Orders which he had to put in Execution, was to take his juſt meaſures for the conveighance of a conſiderable relief into <hi>Caminiec.</hi> To which purpoſe, he went himſelf one day at the head of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95750:10"/>two Hundred Horſe, to view a narrow Lane through which the Convoy was to paſs. But he was no ſooner within ſight of certain hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ways; when he heard a great Noiſe of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, when his Scouts brought him word that a body of four or five hundred <hi>Polonians</hi> had fallen upon two hundred <hi>Tartars</hi> that guarded the cloſe Waggons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> never ſtood to conſider, but march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directly toward the Noiſe, fell with that Fury upon the Squadrons of the Enemy, that he broke 'em at the firſt Charge, ſlew a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber upon the place, while the reſt being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd, made their eſcape to a Wood, whither he thought it not convenient to purſue 'em, but to make immediately up to the Waggons; where he heard the cries of certain perſons in diſtreſs, and preſently caſt his Eye upon four Women, among which there was one in a <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covite</hi> Habit that ſeem'd to be not above Sixteen Years of Age, but ſo wonderfully Beautiful, and ſo accompliſh'd in all outward Perfections, that he could not chooſe but behold her with aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
            <p>The Fright ſhe had been in, the Emotion of her Spirits, which the Noiſe and Surprize of the Skirmiſh had occaſion'd within her, did but ſerve to redouble the lilly whiteneſs and liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her Complexion. <hi>Soliman,</hi> who was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally Amorous, and who at that very inſtant felt in his Heart a more than ordinary Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, paid her all the reſpects that his Character
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95750:10"/>would permit him, and which the excellency of her Beauty deſerv'd. But if the Charms of this unknown perſon caus'd ſo great a ſurprize in <hi>Soliman,</hi> ſhe became no leſs ſenſible, when ſhe beheld the the goodly Aſpect, the delicate Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaments, and obliging Manners of her Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. He never left the Convoy till he had ſeen her ſafe beyond the narrow paſs, and having ſeen her in the plain, he ſent along with her fifty of his Horſe for her greater Security, with Orders to the Commander of the Party, exactly to inform himſelf, who that aſſable Perſon was, whither ſhe was Travelling, and where ſhe was to make her ſtay.</p>
            <p>After this, <hi>Soliman,</hi> having acquitted himſelf of every thing that his duty requir'd from him, return'd to his Camp. But it was impoſible for him to apply himſelf to any other thoughts then thoſe which the Idea of the unknown Lady had imprinted in his Mind; and his reſtleſsneſs caus'd him to expect with impatience the return of his Detachment, which at length arriv'd; and at the ſame time the Commander brought him an accompt, that the Lady, whom he had ſeen was call'd <hi>Abra-Mulè,</hi> taken about ſix years of Age, in an incurſion made by the <hi>Tartars</hi> into <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis;</hi> that a rich Merchant of <hi>Samarcan</hi> had bred her up, and carefully preſerv'd her for Ten Years together, and that he was t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>velling for <hi>Belgrade</hi> through <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> in order to carry her to the Grand Viſir, <hi>Karah Ibrahim,</hi> but according to all the conjectures by what he could draw
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95750:11"/>from him, his deſign was only to get Letters of Favour from him, for admiſſion to preſent her to the Sultan. That the Convoy and the Waggons ſtaid at <hi>Kolenko,</hi> a Caſtle ſeated within two miles of the Camp, and that they were reſolv'd to ſtop there for one day, to recover the young Lady from the Diſorder into which the Encounter with the <hi>Polonians</hi> had put her.</p>
            <p>Such was the Love that <hi>Soliman</hi> had conceiv'd for this young <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> that the firſt growth of it had made ſuch a deep impreſſion in his Heart, that the laſt part of this Relation was like a clap of Thunder to his Sences. In the midſt of his firſt Thoughts, he perſuaded himſelf, that being Maſter of the Armies through the whole extent of the Frontiers of <hi>Poland,</hi> and both Banks of the <hi>Nieſter,</hi> it would be eaſie for him to find pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to ſtop the farther journey of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Lady, and to proſper the attempts of his Love. But ſo ſoon as he conſider'd, that ſhe was deſign'd for the Sultan, deſpair took poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Soul; nor could all his Wit imagin which way to flatter his Deſires. In the midſt of theſe Agitations he omitted nothing of his Duty, but having iſſu'd forth his neceſſary Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, he was ready to retire into his Cabinet, that he might ſurrender himſelf with more Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility to his amorous Contemplations, when word was brought him that the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant deſir'd to kiſs his Hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Murſa,</hi> for that was the name of the <hi>Tartar</hi> was no ſooner arriv'd at <hi>Kolenko,</hi> but after he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95750:11"/>had taken all the requiſite Precautions for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of his Company, he bethought himſelf, that it not only behov'd him to pay his acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement to the Seraskier, but that he might obtain from his generoſity Letters of Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation to the Viſir, and the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> with paſs-ports requiſite for the croſſing of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania;</hi> and to the end that his Compliments and his Preſents might be the more graciouſly accepted, he would needs have 'em accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a few lines from <hi>Abra-Mulè,</hi> and a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in her Name.</p>
            <p>Upon the propoſal which he made the fair <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> ſhe fell into a Diſorder, which might have eaſily unravell'd the thoughts of her Heart, had not the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant attributed to her modeſty the ruddy Blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes that ſpread themſelves in her Cheeks. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liman's</hi> victorious Merit, at the firſt ſight, had caſt into her Soul the Sparkles of a Paſſion, which the condition ſhe was in, commanded her to ſtiflle. On the other ſide it was no ſmall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to her, that it was in her power to oblige him to renew her in his Memory, by means of an opportunity, that put neither her Chaſtity nor her Modeſty in any hazard; only ſhe was afraid leaſt her Heart ſhould dictate too much to her Pen. This combat ſuſpended her Reſolution. But at length <hi>Murſa,</hi> who was to her inſtead of a Father, preſſing her with the Authority of a Maſter, ſhe took her Pen and wrote the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lines.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95750:12"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Abra-Mulè</hi> to Soliman Baſha, Seraskier.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am too much beholding to your Valour, not to join my particular acknowledgment with that of <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi>'s; I obey'd him with delight. I could willingly deſire, Sir, you could but apprehend to what a degree this Obligation is engrav'd in my Soul: the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of it ſhall be Eternal. But in regard I have only good wiſhes, wherewith to acknowledge ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a ſervice, they will never be to my ſatisfaction, till Heaven has beſtow'd upon you all the Happineſs which you deſerve, and which I wiſh you.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>ABRA-MULE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter ſhe accompany'd with a rich Scan of Gold Tiſſu, Embroider'd with Pearl, the work of her own hands. <hi>Murſa</hi> alſo took along with him a magnificent Turbant, and with twenty Horſe arriv'd at the <hi>Seraskier</hi>'s Camp.</p>
            <p>'Tis no hard matter to imagin how much to his ſatisfaction he was receiv'd. <hi>Murſa</hi> gave <hi>Soliman</hi> to underſtand that <hi>Abra-Mulè</hi> was the Daughter of a <hi>Boyar</hi> or <hi>Muſcovite</hi> Nobleman whoſe name was <hi>Mulè-Alexowitz,</hi> who being too confident of maintaining his Ground againſt an Inundation of <hi>Tartars</hi> into his Caſtle of <hi>Sinolo</hi> ſeated upon the Frontiers, had the misfortun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be taken by ſtorm, to have all that he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> plunder'd, burnt or put to the Sword; that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95750:12"/>Boyar himſelf was ſlain in the firſt heat of the onſet; that a common <hi>Tartar</hi> having his Scimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lifted up to <hi>Maſſaker Abra-Mulè,</hi> an Officer compaſſionating the tender Beauty of the Infant, ſtopt his Arm; that the ſame Officer took her as part of his ſhare, and ſold her to himſelf; that ſhe was bred up with his Daughter, and that her Beauty every day increaſing, and being arriv'd at an accompliſh'd perfection, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to make a preſent of it to the Sultan; that he had already written to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, both to <hi>Kara Ibrahim,</hi> the Grand Viſir, and to the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> who had return'd him favourable anſwers, with orders to ſet forward with all ſpeed; that he was expected at <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> where the Sultan intended to ſpend the Summer; and that he made all the haſt that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he could. That his Inſtructions were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Orders from the Viſir at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he beſought <hi>Soliman</hi> to ſecond him yet farther with his Letters of Recommendation.</p>
            <p>This Recical not a little perplex'd the <hi>Seraski<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and his Grief would have more loudly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted it ſelf, had not <hi>Abra-Mulè</hi>'s Letter ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what calm'd his Sorrows. What an unexpected joy! What Agitations did he not feel within his throbbing Heart! though it contain'd no more then a bare Compliment, he thought he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd ſomethings in it that flatter'd both his Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination and his Love. He kindly accepted the preſents, promis'd <hi>Murſa</hi> whatever he demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and while his attendants were entertaining
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95750:13"/>the Merchant with uſual Refreſhments, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took himſelf to his Cabinet, and return'd the following anſwer more circumſpect out of Policy, then his Love would otherwiſe have prompted him to make.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Soliman Seraskier <hi>to the incomparable</hi> Abra-Mulè.</head>
                  <p>THE little ſervice which my good Fortune gave me an oppertunity to perform, did not deſerve ſo great a Recompence as that which I receive from the faireſt and moſt amiable perſon in the World. I will give my ſelf the true delight of coming my ſelf to thank you for ſo much goodneſs ſo little expected, and to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you whatever lies within my power. I hope then, to let you underſtand, that there cannot be any perſon more devoted to your ſervice then is</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Soliman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The <hi>Seraskier</hi> deliver'd this Letter open to <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa,</hi> and told him withall, that ſince he was to ſtay a whole day at <hi>Kolenco,</hi> he would be there upon the morrow, on purpoſe with a ſmall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to alleviate the hardſhips he had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd in a toilſom Journey: That it was the leaſt he could do to wait upon a Perſon deſign'd for his Maſter's Embraces; in the mean time he would take care for the making ready ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as ſhould render more ſupportable the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigues of their enſuing Travels.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95750:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Murſa</hi> departed very well ſatisfied, and <hi>Soliman</hi> retiring, took his Letter, and read it over and over again, and kiſſing it as often as he caſt his eyes upon it, Can it be poſſible fair <hi>Abra,</hi> ſaid he, that the Remembrance of <hi>Soliman</hi> ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be eternal in thy Memory? But, anſwer'd he to himſelf, to what purpoſe would that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance ſerve, but to render me more miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable! Stifle thy Love unfortunate <hi>Soliman,</hi> thou wouldſt diſpute thy Right in <hi>Abra</hi> with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but thy Sultan; but in conteſting with thy Maſter, there is nothing that can flatter thy hope. Stifle then, this Love, before it gets too powerful a Dominion over thee.</p>
            <p>After this, he walkt to and fro in a profound ſilence, till at length his Paſſion getting the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand. Well! ſaid he, What ſignifies it? Maugre my deſpair, can I prevail upon my ſelf to ſay I will not Love her? No, no,—I will love her—and make known to her the Paſſion which ſhe has kindled in my Heart: What is to be done, ſhould ſhe by chance love me? But Oh—that's the Queſtion. A thouſand Accidents, which I foreſee not, may favour the ſucceſs of my Love. The <hi>Kiſter Agaſi</hi> is my ſure Friend, he is the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Serraglio: <hi>Mahomet</hi> loves me; nor is it a new thing for the Sultans to honour their Favourites with Wives out of their Serraglio: The Sultaneſs <hi>Aſſeki</hi> is jealous: <hi>Mahomet</hi> may be hinderd from fixing his Affection upon <hi>Abra.</hi> Laſtly, there is nothing but what my be hop'd for from Time, and my Intregues.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:95750:14"/>
            <p>With theſe Chimera's he flatter'd his Paſſion, and then revolving in his memory the ſame Thoughts over and over again, he conſider'd, that before he let himſelf looſe to theſe Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations it was to be preſuppos'd that he was belov'd by <hi>Abra,</hi> and after he had been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time reflecting upon this, at length he reſolv'd to try whither he could gain her, and then to carry on his Intrigues, as Accidents and Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities ſhould offer.</p>
            <p>Having ſpent the night in theſe reſtleſs Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulations of his contending thoughts, he ſent his Servants the next morning to <hi>Kolenco</hi> to make ready, with all the magnificence that poſſible could be, the Entertainment which he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated: he apparell'd himſelf as ſumptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as poſſibly he could, girded his Veſt with the Scarf that <hi>Abra</hi> had preſented him, put on <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi>'s Turban, and accompanied with eight or ten of the principal Officers of his Army, to the end his Journey might be the leſs ſuſpected, or rather that it might be lookt upon as a piece of Honour pay'd the Sultan, he arriv'd at <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenco.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Collation was <hi>Superb;</hi> the Dances after the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> manner; Wreſtling, Racing, and the reſt of the Divertiſments were ſucceſsfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd; and toward Sun-ſet a <hi>Promenade</hi> in a little Grove ſerv'd for an Interval, in expectation of the Fire-works that were to enlighten the firſt Appearances of darkneſs.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95750:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> could not till then meet with an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to diſcourſe <hi>Abra;</hi> but then he gave her his hand; and while the Officers made their ſeveral Applications to other Women, the whole Company perceiv'd themſelves near the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into a long green Arbour. <hi>Soliman</hi> led in the young <hi>Muſcovite;</hi> and <hi>Murſa,</hi> who had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven her Directions to requeſt ſomething of the Seraskier, which he durſt not preſume to ask himſelf, kept his poſt, out of reſpect, at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Arbour, and his Example obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all the reſt to ſeperate themſelves, ſome one way, ſome another, <hi>Soliman</hi> caus'd <hi>Abra</hi> to ſeat her ſelf upon a Bank of Turf, and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that though he might be ſeen, he could not be heard by the Merchant, he thought it behov'd him not to loſe an Opportunity ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to his Paſſion. Preſently therefore with a low Voice, and a paſſionate and tender Look.</p>
            <p>Fair <hi>Abra,</hi> ſaid he, how dear has my good Fortune coſt me! that I ſhould have the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to come to your Relief, but that that ſame ſuccour ſhould prove the only occaſion of my Torments. I ought indeed, to bury 'em in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence from yee; the Reſpect which your Eyes Imprint, the Grandeur to which you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, and my duty to the Sultan, all theſe Conſiderations ſhould lock up my Tongue, but my Love o'rerules me. Perhaps I may never have but this moment of my life to let you know it. But though I were ſure it would prove my
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95750:15"/>Ruin, I could not reſolve with my ſelf to looſe ſo happy a Minute,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra,</hi> who till then had never perceiv'd in all the <hi>Seraskier's</hi> Conduct, other then reſpectful Warineſs, by means of which he had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood ſo well to conceal the Sentiments which he reveal'd to her, did not expect ſo lively a Declaration of his Love. Wherefore, as much inclin'd as her heart might be to pleaſe it ſelf with the thoughts of being belov'd by a Perſon whom ſhe found to be altogether Admirable, yet was ſhe toſt with a moſt terrible Combat between the Pleaſure of knowing the effect of her Charms, and the fear of explaining her ſelf upon a ſubject of which ſhe her ſelf was ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            <p>A ſuddain Bluſh redoubl'd the Luſter of her Complexion; ſhe caſt her Eyes upon the ground, for fear they ſhould betray the trouble of her mind, and with the ſame reſtriction upon her Voice.</p>
            <p>Heaven, Sir, ſaid ſhe, does not conſult our Hearts to regulate our Deſtinies. I am a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctine Sacrific'd to the intereſt of a <hi>Tartar;</hi> would you hinder me from ſuffering my ſelf to be led without murmuring to the Altar? Alas, as free a Woman as I ſhall enter into the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> I ſhall endure perhaps but too much pain to ſee my ſelf the ſlave of falſe Grandeur that will ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing to one that contemns it as I do; and would you labour to redouble the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are preparing for me in that place?</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95750:15"/>
            <p>Ah, Madam, reply'd <hi>Soliman,</hi> did you look upon as a ſurpluſage of pains what I have ſaid to yee, how happy ſhould I be; ſince then I might hope that my Love would make ſome impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in your Heart, The word is ſlipt from my Mouth, and I can no longer hold my Tongue. I love ye Madam, I Adore ye, I Burn, but with a Fire that never can be extinguiſh'd. Ah, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, what is there that I would not ſtrive to merit, ſo that I might not be indifferent to your Affection!</p>
            <p>Here <hi>Soliman</hi> ſtopt, but finding that <hi>Abra</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd ſilent, and that with her Eyes fix'd upon the Ground, ſhe ſeem'd to be in a kind of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty what anſwer to return; Speak, faireſt <hi>Abra,</hi> continu'd he, ſpeak, or give me my Deaths wound, and perceiving ſome Tears drop from her Eyes, yes, charming <hi>Abra,</hi> repeated he, I love ye beyond all that man can Love, I A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore yee: Can you look with indifferency upon a Paſſion ſo tender and ſo lively?</p>
            <p>Ah, Sir, anſwer'd the <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> with a ſigh that ſhe could nor reſtrain, had your Paſſion been indifferent to me, I ſhould have told ye but too much ere now. I never had ſo great a dread, added ſhe, of being ſacrific'd to the Paſſions of an unknown perſon, as ſince I know that man of all the world moſt worthy to poſſeſs my heart. I now have ſaid too much, Sir, but time which is to you ſo Precious, and your Eternal Separation make me forget my ſelf, and put me quite to Shame. I Bluſh for my Weakneſs, in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95750:16"/>not being able to conceal the Tryumph of your Merit. However, Sir, abuſe not this my Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, it has betray'd me. But ſince Heaven has ſurrounded this Paſſion with an invincible Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle, let us ſtifle it in its Birth, and let not this ſecret be known to yee, for any other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then to forger it.</p>
            <p>Who I? Madam, reply'd <hi>Soliman,</hi> I muſt then forget the only thing that can procure my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. If Heaven obſtructs the accompliſhment of my deſires, at leaſt it ſhall not hinder me from eaſing my Torments with the pleaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that your Heart is not inſenſible of my Love. Leave the reſt to time, to my Fortune, and to my Induſtry. I ſhall be at <hi>Adrianople</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Campaign is over; truſt to the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> I will inſtruct him what he is to do in my behalf, and confide in the inviolable fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Soliman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you; Sir, ſince your Merit has forc'd me to betray the impreſſion which it has made in my heart, aſſure your ſelf that it ſhall be my chief delight to preferr you before all the Crowns of the Earth; and that all my Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Horrors of my cloſe confinement ſhall be to find that you are conſtant.</p>
            <p>The fear of rendring ſuſpicious a longer Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe made <hi>Abra</hi> riſe. The <hi>Seraskier</hi> led her by the hand, they rejoyn'd <hi>Murſa,</hi> and all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany being come together, they went to the Banks of a River, upon which there were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd a great many Fire-works; while a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95750:16"/>Collation under a ſtately open Tent by the River ſide concluded the Divertiſements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> departed a thouſand times more ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd then at his firſt Arrival; and the next morning <hi>Murſa</hi> continu'd his Journey, having obtain'd of the <hi>Seraskier</hi> whatever he could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. But if he travell'd with contentment, the nearer he advanc'd to his journeys End, the more mortal was <hi>Abra</hi>'s Grief for the remoteneſs of a Separation, ſo much the more dreadful to her, becauſe ſhe could not foreſee any means or way by which ſhe ſhould ever meet again with the perſon who already ſhe lov'd ſo tenderly, and with ſuch a ſincere Paſſion.</p>
            <p>'Twas no hard matter ſoon to perceive the Melancholly that began to weaken her, and which was aſcrib'd to the fatigues of a long Journey. But her ſlave <hi>Sarai,</hi> who had always attended her as a Governeſs, penetrated into the true reaſon of it; and in regard ſhe lay by her ſide, her Sighs could not eſcape her. She alſo obſerv'd, that ever ſince the morning of her departure from <hi>Kolenco,</hi> ſhe had in the Agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of her Dreams ſeveral times repeated the Name of <hi>Soliman,</hi> ſo that having a ſingular kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for this Amiable Virgin, and on the other ſide the merit of the <hi>Seraskier,</hi> and his Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty having an influence upon her Mind, ſhe ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd to puſh her Penetration a little farther, and to ſeek ſome remedy for the pains her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs endur'd.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95750:17"/>
            <p>With this purpoſe the Night following when they were alone, and that ſhe heard her Sigh more violently, ſhe drew near her Bed, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing her, I love ye tenderly, my dear <hi>Abra,</hi> ſaid ſhe, I love yee tenderly, and will you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal any longer from me what I already know too well? Open your ſelf to me, and expect from my Fidelity and my Deſcretion whatever my zeal can offer yee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra,</hi> ſurpriz'd at this Diſcourſe, anſwer'd only with a Sigh. But <hi>Sarai</hi> embrac'd her more cloſely, and conjur'd her with ſo much importunity, and after ſuch an affectionate man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to truſt her with what ſhe could no longer conceal from her, that at length <hi>Abra,</hi> melting into Tears lay'd open her Heart. <hi>Sarai</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, promis'd her all aſſiſtance, and aſſur'd her, that if ſhe had a thouſand Lives, ſhe would venture 'em all to make her happy.</p>
            <p>From that very moment <hi>Abra</hi> appear'd more blithe, as if by entruſting her ſecret, ſhe had diſcharg'd her ſelf of ſome weighty Burthen. And in regard that <hi>Soliman</hi> ſought allways im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginable with ſafety to convey his mind in writing to <hi>Abra, Sarai</hi> ſpar'd him the fruitleſs trouble which he put himſelf to, while he thought to accompliſh his deſires by any other aſſiſtance then hers.</p>
            <p>A correſpondence of that Importance hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Life both of the one and the other, and therefore to avoid all Danger, it was agreed, that the <hi>Seraskier's</hi> Letters ſhould be ſo contriv'd,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95750:17"/>as if he had an Affection for <hi>Zaid,</hi> who was <hi>Sarai</hi>'s Neece, and Beautiful beſide, and that <hi>Sarai</hi> her ſelf ſhould write <hi>Abra</hi>'s Letters, in <hi>Zaids</hi> Name. The intercourſe was thus ſettl'd upon the third day after the Separation of the two Lovers, and the firſt Letter that <hi>Abra</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from the <hi>Seraskier,</hi> contain'd theſe kind Expreſſions.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Soliman <hi>to</hi> Zaid.</head>
                  <p>TO Love every day, to be ſenſible of the ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Separation from us of what we love much more then our ſelves, and not to know whether ever ſhe ſhall meet again; what an Affliction, Adorable <hi>Zaid,</hi> what Torments are theſe! But it would be much more cruel, if at the ſame time I ſhould have any reaſon to doubt the Sincerity of your Words. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the promiſe you have made me, and be aſſur'd, that if I love you more then it is poſſible for all other men together to do, my Fidelity is equal to my Love, and that nothing ſhall ever change the Heart of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>SOLIMAN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra</hi> receiv'd this Billet from <hi>Sarai</hi>'s Hands, and Dictated to her the following Anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:95750:18"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Zaid <hi>to</hi> Soliman Seraskier.</head>
                  <p>MY Aunt deliver'd me your Letter, which has afforded me the only Pleaſure I have had ſince I loſt the ſight of your Perſon. What ſorrows do thoſe Minutes coſt me every day, which once enjoy'd are now no more to be expected! Yet is it written in Heaven that they ſhall nere return! Love, Sir, Love on; but let your Love be ne'r ſo true, be aſſur'd it equals not my love for you, and if your Fidelity be in Violable, my Conſtancy ſhall be Eternal. Pity my Fate, and think often of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>ZAID.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Theſe Letters were attended by ſome others; and in regard that <hi>Soliman</hi> in his ſecond teſtify'd a great deſire to ſee <hi>Abra</hi> once again, <hi>Sarai</hi>'s Advice was that ſhe ſhould fain her ſelf ſick, to the end they might be forc'd to ſtop in a kind of a Caſtle ſeated upon the Edge of a Forreſt. The meaſures taken by <hi>Sarai</hi> were put in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and the <hi>Seraskier</hi> being fully inform'd of <hi>Sarai</hi>'s contrivance, he took Poſt by the means of lay'd Horſes; and under pretences which he never wanted, arriv'd at the place appointed; where he diſguiz'd himſelf in the Habit of a <hi>Dervis,</hi> or one of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Prieſts; in great Veneration among thoſe People, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly thought to be endu'd with a power to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95750:18"/>cure all ſorts of Sickneſs by reading in private certain Chapters of the <hi>Alchoran,</hi> laid upon the head of the ſick Perſon. <hi>Sarai</hi> therefore had prepar'd all things ready for the Applications of the <hi>Dervis</hi> to <hi>Abra</hi>'s Diſtemper, and the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious <hi>Murſa</hi> was fallen into the ſnare, ſo that 'twas no hard matter to introduce <hi>Soliman</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that diſguize, which <hi>Murſa</hi> ſo little ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that ſeeing him coming at a Diſtance, he fell with his Face upon the Ground, and made all his Servants do as much, while the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Saint paſt forward with a great Alchoran, which he held open, and reſting upon his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, as upon a Desk, to the end he might the better hide his Face.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> being thus enter'd into <hi>Abra</hi>'s Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, thought it not convenient to ſpend his time in reading the Alchoran, but throwing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at <hi>Abra</hi>'s Knees, and embracing 'em, who would have thought, ſaid he, fair <hi>Abra,</hi> who would have thought that I ſhould ever have been ſo happy to ſee you again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra,</hi> that ſhe might oblige him to a poſture more becoming his Grandeur, ſeated her ſelf upon a Couch that was cloſe by; but <hi>Soliman</hi> ſtill continuing with one Knee upon the Ground, and perceiving that <hi>Saria</hi> was retir'd to have an Eye at the Door, he took both her hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his own, and continuing his Diſcourſe. No, No, Madam, No, ſaid he, I no longer queſtion your Love, ſince without any he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſcruple you have ventur'd all to afford
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95750:19"/>me this alleviation of my Pains. Ah, Madam, what a Pleaſure it it, what a Satisfaction to me to ſee you once again! Sir, reply'd <hi>Abra,</hi> if the Pleaſure of ſeeing what we love be to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by love, your Joy is not ſuperiour to mine. But with what bitterneſſes is this ſecret Pleaſure intermix'd, when we conſider that 'tis but for a Moment, which will be attended with a long and perhaps perpetual Separation.</p>
            <p>Hope better Madam, reply'd <hi>Soliman,</hi> and ſince our Prophet himſelf affords me this day by the help of this Diſguiſe, an Opportunity of ſeeing you, be aſſur'd that he approves our Fires, and that he will direct us to find our which way to enjoy our Affection with more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. I come here chiefly to inſtruct yee what meaſures are to be taken, to prevent our being expos'd to the Sultan's paſſions. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe here is a Letter to the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> which <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rai</hi> ſhall take care to deliver him, before he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives thoſe wherewith <hi>Murſa</hi> is entruſted; and provided you can but preſerve me your heart till I return to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> and that the <hi>Kiſler</hi> does but prevent your being ſeen by <hi>Mahomet,</hi> I will ſet all Engins at work, and I preſume ſo much upon his Highneſs's favour, that I deſpair not to obtain you as his own gift.</p>
            <p>If it only depends upon my Conſtancy, ſaid <hi>Abra,</hi> to avoid the Sultan, and enjoy your Love, you may rely upon me, Sir, that nothing ſhall be wanting on my part to proſper the ſucceſs of your Paſſion: But take care, Sir, that I may
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95750:19"/>not be depriv'd in the Serraglio of the comfort of having my faithful <hi>Sarai</hi> about me; my Heart is in her hands, and ſhe will be of great Uſe to us.</p>
            <p>This, reply'd <hi>Soliman,</hi> is one of the principal Motives of my Letter: for I do not diſcover to the <hi>Kiſter</hi> the ſecret of ſo dangerous a Paſſion. I referr that till we come to diſcourſe together: But I ſend to him only to do me thoſe Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, which I can only expect from his Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry in favouring my deſires. He is Maſter of the Serraglio; he ſhall keep <hi>Sarai</hi> with yee, no doubt of it; and he ſhall do nothing without conſulting her. And to the end, that by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what I have written, you may the better be able to underſtand how to govern your Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, here is a Copy of it. <hi>Abra</hi> took the Copy, and calling <hi>Sarai,</hi> read the following Lines.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:95750:20"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Soliman Seraskier</hi> to the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Iſouf <hi>Kiſler Agaſi.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>YOur Mightineſs will receive by the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Merchant <hi>Murſa</hi> Letters of Recommendation, to the end the Preſent which he deſigns to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Noble and Vertuous Slave <hi>Abra-Mulè,</hi> may be the more graciouſly accepted. You have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways found me to be your Friend; and I know the Reaſons of your being ſupported by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Sultaneſs <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> which obliges me, as a Confident, to admoniſh you not to be too forward in expoſing this new Commer to the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s view till I return to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> at what time I will inform you of every thing. In the mean time fail not to let <hi>Sarai</hi> continue with her; to the end ſhe may be ſerviceable to you, in calming <hi>Abra</hi>'s impatience to arrive at that Honour to which <hi>Karah Ibrahim's</hi> Cabal deſignes her. The Advice is of great Importance, therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it not.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After the reading of this Letter, <hi>Soliman</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed <hi>Abra</hi> and <hi>Sarai,</hi> in all the ſecret In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treagues of the Serraglio, and how it behov'd 'em to manage their Affairs; ſo that they might be able to ſecond whatever he ſent to the <hi>Kiſler.</hi> After this, two the Lovers fell into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate diſcourſe, wherein they omitted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to give each other reciprocal Marks of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95750:20"/>their moſt tender and ardent Paſſion. At length the time which the <hi>Dervis</hi> uſually employ with their ſick Patients being almoſt ſpent, and the fatal Moment of Separation approaching, <hi>Abra</hi> took out of a little Trunk three of her own Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traitures, and requeſted <hi>Soliman</hi> to make choice of one. He took that which he thought moſt like her, and at the ſame time <hi>Abra</hi> threw the other two into the fire.</p>
            <p>What d' yee do, Madam, cry'd <hi>Soliman,</hi> why d' yee ſo profuſely deſtroy the Images of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Maſter-piece. In regard I have but one Heart, reply'd <hi>Abra,</hi> and that never any Perſon in the World ſhall enjoy it but your ſelf, for whom would you have me preſerve thoſe other Portraitures? I offer 'em up to that which I give you, and which I beg you to keep; as I ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice all the reſt of the Earth to the only Love I have for <hi>Soliman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Seraskier</hi> admir'd the Delicacy of <hi>Abra</hi>'s Heart, and kiſſing the Hand from which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Portraiture, how ſweet a thing it is, Madam, ſaid he, how ſweet a thing it is to be belov'd after ſo tender and delicate a manner. I accept this precious pledge of your Love, I will preſerve it till Death, and it ſhall be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Teſtimony of my Conſtancy. After this the <hi>Seraskier</hi> took leave of <hi>Abra,</hi> who could not reſtrain her Tears, and at the ſame time taking his Head between her Arms, and preſſing it cloſe to her Boſom, ſhe gave him a kiſs upon the Fore-head, and then permitted him to take the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95750:21"/>ſame liberty upon each hand. Which done, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liman</hi> roſe up, and after he had prevail'd with <hi>Sarai</hi> to accept a magnificent preſent in Jewels, he left the Chamber with the ſame Ceremony as he enter'd in, <hi>Murſa</hi> attending him with a great Train to the Gate of the Caſtle. <hi>Abra</hi> recover'd her Health; the Reputation of this <hi>Dervis</hi> was ſpread abroad, and <hi>Soliman</hi> quitting his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Habit, took Poſt again, and return'd to the Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Murſa</hi> extreamly ſatisfy'd with the pretended Miracle of the Alchoran, which redoubl'd his Superſtition, departed the next morning, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding proſperouſly in his journey, while <hi>Abra</hi> comforted her ſelf in <hi>Sarai</hi>'s Boſom, with read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Letters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ich ſhe receiv'd from time to time directed to <hi>Zaid,</hi> and ſpending ſome nights in returning anſwers to 'em.</p>
            <p>They croſs'd <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> travelling eaſie Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, and <hi>Michael Abaffi</hi> defraying their charges all along; and being arriy'd at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> at a time when <hi>Karah Ibrahim</hi> was there, obtain'd <hi>Murſa</hi> from him, whatever Letters of Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation he deſir'd. At length he got to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> where the Sultan had been ſince the Spring, that he might be ne'r at hand to iſſue forth his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for the motion of his Troops, and that he might be the more punctually inform'd of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that fell out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sarai,</hi> whoſe Diligence inclin'd her to ſpare for nothing, and who underſtood, that in the Serraglio all things were mov'd by the Springs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95750:21"/>of many, was no ſooner arriv'd there, but ſhe won the heart of the <hi>Kiſlers</hi> firſt <hi>Dragoman,</hi> or Interpreter, and caus'd <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Letter to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd to that powerful Eunuch, before <hi>Murſa</hi> had made any progreſſes toward his obtaining Audience. The <hi>Kiſler</hi> being thus anticipated, kept the <hi>Tartar</hi> above two Months before he ſuffer'd <hi>Abra</hi> to be introduc'd into the <hi>Serraglio;</hi> beſides, that he found a way to bring her in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt, and among a Huddle of eight or ten o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which various <hi>Baſha's</hi> had ſent, and made choice of a day that the Sultan was vext and out of humour upon the receit of ſome ill News; ſo that <hi>Mohomet</hi> being taken up with the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom Conſultations, wherein the taking of <hi>Neuhanſal</hi> had engag'd the whole <hi>Divan,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the raiſing of the Siege of <hi>Gran,</hi> which the <hi>Turks</hi> had fruitleſsly attempted, and the loſs of a Battel fought within two Leagues of that place, and being more over continually beſieg'd by the Sultaneſs <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> and <hi>Abra</hi> never ſeeking to expoſe her ſelf, it was no difficult thing for the <hi>Kiſler</hi> to put her into an Appartment out of the way, and keep her out of <hi>Mahomet's</hi> Eye.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Abra</hi> avoided the ſight, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the love of the Sultan, till the end of the Campaign, ſhe found her ſelf expos'd to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Amour, which though at firſt it appear'd leſs dangerous, yet the Conſequences of it were moſt terribly fatal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet</hi> kept his Brothers under a kind of Confinement, where nevertheleſs they had free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95750:22"/>enough. He forc'd 'em to attend him in all his Progreſſes, and they were then in the <hi>Serra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio</hi> at <hi>Adrianople</hi> ſerv'd as Princes in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Appartments; and the <hi>Sultan</hi> who would not deprive 'em of their Pleaſures, but was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing however they ſhould have any Children, took care that they ſhould not be ſuffer'd to come at any Women, but ſuch as were paſt Child bearing; yet that they ſhould provide for 'em the handſomeſt that could be found out at thoſe years.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> who, as I have ſaid, was a handſom perſon, notwithſtanding he ſeem'd ſo addicted to the ſtudy of the <hi>Alchoran,</hi> was of an amorous Complection, and was not ſatisfi'd with the ſuperannuated Miſtreſſes with which they endeavour'd to amuſe him. He was wily, and full of diſſimulation, and having acquir'd a perfect confidence with an Elderly Woman, call'd <hi>Marama,</hi> who was impos'd upon him for one of his Bed-fellows, he had ſo much influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence over her, as to engage her to ſupply him by dextrous Intreagues, with younger paſtimes then thoſe to which he was forc'd to confine himſelf, and ſhe had already ſucceeded in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Negotiations that requir'd a moſt nice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.</p>
            <p>She had her Appartiment in the ſame Gallery where <hi>Abra</hi> had hers; and in regard ſhe was extreamly Inſinuating, full of Flattery, together with an Anticipating and frolick Wit, ſhe ſoon ſtruck in with the young <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> and faſten'd
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95750:22"/>her ſelf to her in a ſtrict familiarity, which their near Nighbourhood allow'd of, and which the <hi>Kiſler</hi> favour'd, to the end ſhe might be taken up with divertiſements, that might hinder her from thinking of the Sultan.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marama</hi> had no ſooner knit the knot of this familiarity, but having found out that <hi>Abra</hi> had no ambitious deſign of making her ſelf known to the <hi>Sultan,</hi> it came into her Head to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tregue her with <hi>Soliman.</hi> To which purpoſe ſhe made ſuch a lively Deſcription of the young <hi>Muſcovite</hi> to the youthful Prince, that without any trouble ſhe infus'd into him a violent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee her; and on the other ſide, ſhe made uſe of all her Wit in magnifying to <hi>Abra</hi> the merits of <hi>Soliman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to create an opportunity for the Prince to ſatisfie his Eyes with the ſight of an Object which ſhe had painted to him adorn'd with ſo many Accompliſhments, ſhe obtain'd leave of the <hi>Kiſler</hi> to give a Collation to five or ſix of her Friends in the Sultaneſs's <hi>Validès</hi> private Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and ſhe ſo order'd her Buſineſs, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage <hi>Abra</hi> to be one of her Gueſts.</p>
            <p>The Collation was ſerv'd up at the end of an Alley that was overlook'd by a Croſs-bar'd win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Soliman's</hi> appartiment, who from thence had a full view of the <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> whom he found infinitely more beautiful then <hi>Marama</hi> had ſet her forth to be; and of a ſuddain fell ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently in love with her, that his dear confident coming in the Evening to viſit him, he ſhut
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95750:23"/>himſelf up with her, and cloſely embracing her, I am a dead Man, my dear <hi>Marama,</hi> ſaid he, if you afford not ſome aſſwagement to that love which you have kindl'd, and which can only be expected from your addreſs and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p>This Relief reply'd <hi>Marama,</hi> depends not upon me; I have found the way to bleſs your Eyes with an Object that moſt deſerves the love of the greateſt Prince in the World. This is but the firſt ſtep; it behoves me now to ſound her Heart, which ſeems to me but very indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent as to all ſorts of Pleaſures, and leſs inclin'd to love then any other Paſſion. But the main difficulty is for you to ſee her, and ſpeak to her. However leave that to Time and my Diligence, and be aſſur'd that I ſhall omit nothing to bring it to paſs.</p>
            <p>This Promiſe ſomething quieted <hi>Soliman</hi>'s firſt Diſturbances; he rely'd upon <hi>Marama</hi>'s cunning, and in the mean time not believing that a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Serraglio could hold out againſt the Love of an <hi>Ottoman</hi> Prince, He flatter'd his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with that ſuccess which was at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from him.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Marama</hi> united her ſelf more cloſely to the young <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> and by her Aſſidui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhe alſo inſinuated her ſelf into <hi>Sarai</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and at length ſhe carry'd her ſelf ſo pliant, that <hi>Abra</hi> who ſought only for Paſtimes to conceal and aſſwage her Anxieties, could not live without her company.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:95750:23"/>
            <p>When ſhe found her ſelf ſo well ſettl'd in a heart which ſhe thought void of Love, ſhe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to infuſe that Paſſion by a general diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the pleaſures that attended the Union of two Perſons in a charming Affection. <hi>Abra</hi> liſten'd to her, and ſeem'd to give Credit to her diſcourſe, becauſe that all ſhe ſaid to her flatter'd her Inclinations for the <hi>Seraskier:</hi> And <hi>Marama,</hi> who was perſwaded ſhe had made ſome Impreſſion upon her Soul, imagin'd that nothing remain'd for her to do, but only by ſome Artifice to get <hi>Soliman</hi> and <hi>Abra</hi> together, which ſhe thought might be eaſily brought to paſs.</p>
            <p>The body of the Building wherein were the Appartiments of <hi>Abra, Marama,</hi> and a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other Women, was directly oppoſite to that wherein the Princes were lodg'd; and to prevent their Communication, and ſeeing one another, a very thick and high Wall divided the Court, by which they were ſeparated.</p>
            <p>The body of the Building wherein were the Appartiments of <hi>Abra, Marama,</hi> and a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other Women, was directly oppoſite to that wherein the Princes were lodg'd; and to prevent their Communication, and ſeeing one another, a very thick and high Wall divided the Court, by which they were ſeparated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amurath,</hi> who built thoſe two Structures, or Piles of Lodgings, to be himſelf in the one with the favourite Sultaneſs, and to lodge the moſt beautiful Women of his Serraglio in the other, had contriv'd a private little Gallery under Ground, whereby he might paſs from one Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the other, and avoid the jealous Eyes of the Sultaneſs when he had a mind to viſit his other Women. The Entrance into that Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery jutted upon the Appartment poſſeſs'd by Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> and led to <hi>Marama</hi>'s Cabinet; but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95750:24"/>two Doors a long time ſince made up prohibited the uſe of it.</p>
            <p>To attempt the opening of a place in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio clos'd up, was a Crime ſufficient to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s jealouſie, and to hazard <hi>Soliman</hi>'s life: But in regard it was the only way that <hi>Marama</hi> could think of, ſhe furniſh'd her ſelf with Irons, and falſe Keys, requiſite to make a Breach, and when all things were ready pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd, and concerted with <hi>Soliman,</hi> ſhe engag'd <hi>Abra</hi> to come to her Chamber, and while her Slaves kept <hi>Sarai</hi> in a pleaſing Chat, ſhe led her alone into her Cabinet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> got through, and had hid himſelf behind the hanging that hung before the Out-let of the Gallery: At what time <hi>Marama</hi> having ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Abra</hi> upon a heap of Cuſhions cover'd over with a Carpet, entertain'd her with high Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſes of the marvellous luſtre of her Beauty, the brightneſs of her Eyes, the whiteneſs of her Skin, and all her other Charms; and after that, ſhifting her Diſcourſe, ſhe fell to talk of Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> and cry'd up his Merits to the Skies; inſomuch that the portraiture that ſhe gave of him ſeeming to have a fair reſemblance of the Aire, the lovely Meen, and Lineaments of the Seraskier, the poor betray'd Lady, out of an innocent openneſs of heart, gave her ſelf the liberty to ſignify, that if the ſight of the Prince had not been forbidden by the ſtrict Rules of the Serraglio, her Curioſity might have been prevail'd upon to ſee him.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:95750:24"/>
            <p>Upon thoſe words, <hi>Soliman,</hi> who thought he had met with the Minute proper to make his Appearance, bolted of a ſuddain from behind the Hanging, and falling upon one Knee at <hi>Abra</hi>'s feet, with his Eyes fix'd upon hers, which ſhe caſt toward the ground in a deep ſurprize, that render'd her Immovable, Madam, ſaid he, behold a Prince that burn'd with impatience to behold the moſt wonderful of all perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ever Nature produc'd, and who is come to proſtrate his Heart at your feet, and put his Life in your hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra</hi> who could not recover her ſelf from her Aſtoniſhment, durſt not caſt an Eye upon <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> but upon <hi>Marama</hi> ſhe threw a look that ſeem'd at once both to reproach her Treachery, and bemoan the trouble into which ſhe had plung'd her. A Ruddineſs more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpread it ſelf upon her Cheeks, her whole Body trembl'd, and not knowing what courſe to take under a Circumſtance ſo little expected, ſhe ſtood in a profound ſilence, when <hi>Soliman</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming his firſt Addreſſes, I ſee, Madam, ſaid he, I ſee, that the Happineſs I have had, for the ſight of you, to ſurmount thoſe Obſtacles that would have appear'd invincible to any other Love but that which I have for your ſelf, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends yee; but impute to the power of your Charms, and the tenderneſs of my heart, this Crime that has affrighted yee, and which you will pardon me, when you conſider that no man living can behold thoſe Eyes without ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring 'em.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:95750:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra,</hi> who during this diſorder, felt her an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger augment as her aſtoniſhment began to quit her, caſt a ſmart look upon <hi>Soliman,</hi> and at the ſame time turning again her Eyes away from him, Sir, ſaid ſhe, did you only expoſe my life by an Enterprize ſo dangerous both for you and <hi>Marama,</hi> you ſhould not have ſeen me tremble. But Sir, what iſt you aim at by an Undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no leſs fruitleſs then raſh and indiſcreet? I am not ignorant of the full extent of your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and I pay it the real homage of my Eſteem: But if you have forc'd thoſe Obſtacles that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad you the ſight of me, there yet remains o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers far more invincible, that forbid my heart to entertain a Paſſion that muſt never enter there.</p>
            <p>Oh, Madam, were the Sultan ſo happy as to have touch'd your heart, I might juſtly fear the meeting with an invincible Obſtacle to my Love; but ſince I know that he has never caſt his Eyes upon you, and that you your ſelf are careful to avoid his ſight, what Obſtacle can the Love of a Prince, who adores yee, meet with in a heart ſo free as yours? A Prince, who would ſacrifice the whole Earth to the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of infuſing into your Soul the ſmalleſt Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for him.</p>
            <p>Prince, reply'd <hi>Abra,</hi> whatever liberty <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> gives my heart, you will not find it leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible then if he had the ſole poſſeſſion of it. Stifle therefore a Love that may precipitate yee into a thouſand diſmal Inconveniencies, I am not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95750:25"/>ignorant of the danger to which, at this Inſtant, you have expos'd your ſelf; nor has the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize into which you have put me; or my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation to ſee my ſelf thus betray'd by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rama</hi> ſo clouded my Reaſon, as not to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what I have to do. I eſteem and reſpect yee, Sir, too much to deny yee my ſilence for the ſecurity of your head. Be gon Sir, and do not ruin your ſelf for the ſake of an Amour, where there is no probability of ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>You may, Madam, never have any Affection for me, but I can never ceaſe to have a Love for you. If my pure Flames offend yee, here's my head, deliver it up to my Brother to puniſh the Preſumption of my Adoration.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid <hi>Abra,</hi> a heart like mine, never ſeeks Revenge, and the Injuries done by Love are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways excuſable, nor will I revenge my ſelf of that which yours has done me, but in labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to extinguiſh it: I alſo pardon <hi>Marama</hi>'s Treachery, for the ſake of her friendſhip for you. Require of my heart all the Eſteem that is due to a Prince of extraordinary Merit: 'Tis your due, and I pay it freely. But require not a Love from a heart that is not at Liberty, and which it would be therefore in vain to impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
            <p>Though this ſame mildneſs that <hi>Abra</hi> ſhew'd was only an effect of her Prudence and Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet <hi>Soliman,</hi> who eaſily flatter'd himſelf in his pleaſures, vainly imagin'd that the reaſon why ſhe ſo willingly conſented by her ſilence
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95750:26"/>to conceal an Attempt ſo criminal, was only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Love and his Character had made the firſt Impreſſions in her heart; and judging that he had done enough for the firſt meeting, in having ſhewn himſelf in perſon, and declar'd his Love, he wittily turn'd the Diſcourſe upon other things more general, and after he had ſtay'd ſometime in the Cabinet, he took his leave.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as he was gone, <hi>Marama,</hi> who had the ſame thoughts as he, preſently began to put <hi>Abra</hi> upon a new Diſcourſe of the Prince's love, imagining that ſhe would open her Mind with more freedom to her: But ſhe was ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, by the Reproaches of her Infidelity, and the ſmart Anſwers which ſhe made her, that that there was nothing leſs in her heart then thoſe Inclinations wherewith <hi>Soliman</hi> flatter'd himſelf; and that if ſhe intended to make any farther progreſſes toward the vanquiſhing her Indifferency, or to preſerve the familiarity ſhe had with her, it behov'd her either not to ſay a word more of that Amour, or elſe to make uſe of Artifices more nice and delicate.</p>
            <p>While this Intreague, which in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſſion prov'd ſo fatal to <hi>Mahomet</hi> was taking root in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> the end of an Unſucceſsful Campaign redoubl'd the Sultan's Anxieties.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had the year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore undertaken the ſiege of <hi>Buda;</hi> but the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of his Enemies which he had in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror's Council, and who envy'd thoſe Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:95750:26"/>which ecclips'd their own, caus'd the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage of that Enterprize, by maliciouſly keeping from him thoſe Supplies which were moſt neceſſary for the Attacque of ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a Place, and the ſubſiſtance of his Men. So that wanting every thing, and not being able to hinder <hi>Cheitan Baſha, Serakeire</hi> of the Armies in <hi>Hungary</hi> from releiving it, he was forc'd to raiſe his ſiege.</p>
            <p>Enrag'd at the Succeſs of his Enemies Malice, the next year he took more certain Meaſures, to the end he might not be expos'd to the ſame Inconveniencies, and open'd a Glorious Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign with the ſiege of <hi>Neuhanſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Vizir <hi>Karah Ibrahim,</hi> who rather choſe to employ the Valour of other men, then to act himſelf, and who from <hi>Belgrade</hi> iſſu'd forth all his Orders to all the Armies, in hopes to make a Diverſion, laid ſiege to <hi>Gran.</hi> But in regard the <hi>Turks</hi> found more reſiſtance there then they expected, after they had waſted twelve days in vain they rais'd their ſiege, and joyn'd all their Forces under <hi>Cheitan Serakier,</hi> to oppoſe Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> who without diſcontinuing the ſiege <hi>Newhanſel,</hi> march'd directly with the Body of his Army to decide the deſtiny of the Campaign by the fate of a Battel.</p>
            <p>The Armies came in view of each other with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in three Leagues of <hi>Gran,</hi> there being nothing between 'em but a <hi>Moraſs,</hi> which could not be croſs'd but through narrow Paſſes at a diſtance one from the other; beſides that the <hi>Cheitan</hi> had
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95750:27"/>ſixty thouſand Men; ſo that Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> who had not above forty five, thought it would be a raſh attempt to paſs the <hi>Moraſs</hi> in view of the Enemy, and within the reach of their ſhot, to attacque 'em in their Entrenchemnt. He therefore try'd whether he could engage 'em to paſs it firſt themſelves, which it was not diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to do by two Stratagemes. The one by ſpreading a falſe report, that his Army was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to forty thouſand Men; and the other, by faining a precipitate and falſe retreat.</p>
            <p>This double Stratagem ſucceeded to a wonder: for the <hi>Turks</hi> obſerving the motion of that faign'd retreat, paſs'd the <hi>Moraſs</hi> in the night time. But then Prince <hi>Charles</hi> who march'd ſlowly, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they were got over, fac'd about, Embat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell'd his Army, and having given the left wing to the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and taking the right himſelf, advanc'd toward the Enemy.</p>
            <p>The Onſet was Vigorous on the <hi>Turks</hi> ſide, who thought they had been marching to a Victory, not to a Combat. They charg'd the two Wings three times, and the Principal weight of their Strength falling upon the Right Wing where the Princes of <hi>Conti</hi> and <hi>Roche ſur Yon</hi> fought as Volunteers at the Head of <hi>Lanthiers</hi>'s Squadron, the immoveable ſteadineſs of theſe Princes render'd ineffectual the Enemie's Efforts, and their undaunted Valour contributed not a little to the winning of the Battel.</p>
            <p>The ſight was long and Obſtinate on the <hi>Turks</hi> ſide, who gave ground, and rally'd as often
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95750:27"/>as they were broken, and returning to the Charge, endeavour'd ſtill to Flank the right Wing, where lay the main ſtrength of the Battel; but at length the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> after he had firſt broken and diſpers'd all that ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, fell with his left Wing upon the <hi>Turks,</hi> and put 'em into ſuch a general Confuſion, that being every where Broken they betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to flight, and repaſs'd the <hi>Moraſs,</hi> beyond which they were ſtill purſu'd with the Loſs of Ten thouſand men, and not daring to ſtay in their Entrenchments, never thought themſelves ſafe till they were got under the Cannon of <hi>Buda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this great Victory, <hi>Newhanſel</hi> was taken by Storm, and the Emperour carry'd his Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Arms as far as the <hi>Drave,</hi> ruining the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> and by taking a good Number of other Places, put the <hi>Divan</hi> into ſuch a Conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that upon the falſe Information of <hi>Karah Ibrahim,</hi> whoſe ill Conduct and Cowardiſe had not a little contributed to the Misfortunes of this Campaign, and who was a Mortal Enemy to the famous Count <hi>Tekeli,</hi> they blindly took a Reſolution to ſeize upon that Count at <hi>Waradin;</hi> and to have him carry'd laden with Fetters to <hi>Adrianople.</hi> Which compleated the Ruin of the <hi>Turks</hi> affairs in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Karah Ibrahim</hi> ſoon after attended upon the Sultan, and finding him incens'd at the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of the Campaign, that he might turn the Effects of his Anger upon ſome other Head, ſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95750:28"/>dextrouſly lay'd the Cauſe of all the Summers ill ſucceſs upon the ill Conduct of the <hi>Seraskier Cheitan,</hi> that <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who was naturally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, forgetting the Signal Services which he had done him both in <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Relief of <hi>Buda,</hi> order'd him to loſe his head, which was publickly put in Execution.</p>
            <p>By his Death the Employment of <hi>Seraskier</hi> of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Armies became Vacant; and for the ſupplying it, the <hi>Sultan</hi> caſt his Eyes upon the <hi>Seraskier Soliman,</hi> whom we left upon the Frontiers of <hi>Poland,</hi> and who had promis'd the fair <hi>Abra,</hi> that after the end of the Campaign he would be at <hi>Adrianople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had perform'd his Duty with ſo much conduct and valour, that all the Efforts of the <hi>Polanders</hi> prov'd abortive, and that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their Oppoſition, he had ſupply'd <hi>Caminiec</hi> with a conſiderable Convoy. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his Aſſiduity in the performance of his Duty and his Vigilance, which carry'd him where ever his Preſence might be uſeful, he took his times, by <hi>Sarai</hi>'s Addreſs, and the aſſiſtance of ſome Eunuchs of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> whom ſhe had won to her ſide, to let the fair <hi>Muſcovite</hi> frequently hear from him, while on the other ſide he receiv'd from her no leſs obliging Marks of her fidelity.</p>
            <p>At length, as ſoon as poſſibly he could, he arriv'd at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> and was receiv'd by the <hi>Sultan,</hi> as one who had the greateſt ſhare in his favour, and who alone of all his Generals during
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:95750:28"/>the Campaign had prevented the Misfortunes of ill Succeſs.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as he alighted he had a long and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate conference with the <hi>Sultan,</hi> touching the General State of Affairs, and in regard he was a particular Friend of Count <hi>Tekeli</hi>'s, he viſibly made appear the falſe Steps which they had made, who counſell'd his Arreſt; and from this Accident paſſing to the Grand Viſir's Conduct, who was the Author of that pernicious Advice, he ſo ſenſibly made out all his Miſtakes, that <hi>Mahomet,</hi> in whoſe favour that Miniſter began already to totter, was abſolutely determin'd to degrade him, and at the ſame time to ſatisfy the favourable Inclinations which he had always had for <hi>Soliman;</hi> ſo that the Seal of the Empire was ſoon after taken from <hi>Karah Ibrahim,</hi> and given to <hi>Soliman,</hi> who was declar'd Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir.</p>
            <p>Yet did he not rejoice at his Exaltation ſo much for any other reaſon, as that he now ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s favour would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe him the happineſs which he far more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd; ſeeing that if the Sultans did not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times diſdain to give their own Daughters to their Grand Viſirs, he might well obtain a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger taken out of the <hi>Serraglio.</hi> But he thought it not convenient to be too haſty, before he had taken his right meaſures; he conſider'd with himſelf that in the New dignity which he held, and which would faſten the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi</hi> more cloſely to his Fortunes, he might diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:95750:29"/>to him his love for <hi>Abra,</hi> and that it behov'd him to make, uſe of the Induſtry and Aſſiſtance of that Eunuch, as well as his own Credit to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the main Aim of his Intentions, and to give the Sultan ſome notice of it before hand, ſo ſoon as an Opportunity offer'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra</hi> receiv'd the News at once both of the Arrival of her dear <hi>Soliman,</hi> and of his Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the chief Dignity in the Empire, and <hi>Sarai</hi> it was who brought her the Intelligence into her Cabinet.</p>
            <p>Now tho' ſhe had bin inform'd that he would be in a ſhort time at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> nevertheleſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the reiterated Orders of the Sultan had precipitated his Journey, he prevented the time which he had perfix'd, and this was that which made her more ſenſible of the joyful news which ſhe receiv'd from her dear Confident. She was in hopes ſhe ſhould have heard from him the ſame day; but he could not withdraw himſelf from the Importunate Throngs that crouded to load him with their Homages; nor could he quit the Urgency of thoſe preſſing Orders wherein he ſpent the reſt of the day, and good part of the night.</p>
            <p>At length being with a world of trouble diſengag'd from ſo many ſlaves, the Adorers of his Fortune, about midnight he detain'd the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi</hi> with him, and took him into his private Cabinet, under pretence of moſt Important Orders which he had to impart to him.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:95750:29"/>
            <p>After they had paid to each other what was due to a long and reciprocal Friendſhip, the <hi>Kiſler</hi> gave <hi>Soliman</hi> an Accompt of the Artifices which he had been forc'd to make uſe of, to hinder <hi>Mahomet</hi> from the ſight of <hi>Abra,</hi> and the precautions which he us'd every day, to make the beſt of the warning he had given him in his Letter, but that things could not long remain in the ſame poſture, unleſs recourſe were had to other ways more hazardous. For that within a few days the Sultaneſſes Feſtival was to be kept, and that day all the Women of the Serraglio appear'd in the private Moſquee, with the Habits and Ornaments which the Sultan order'd to be diſtributed among 'em.</p>
            <p>This news was no way pleaſing to the Viſir, however it did not put him quite out of thoſe hopes wherewith he flatter'd himſelf; ſo that at length; after repeated Expreſſions of the Synce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Affection, he open'd his Heart to the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> told him he was paſſionately in love with <hi>Abra,</hi> and that ſhe correſponded with his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kiſler,</hi> ſurpriz'd at the acknowledgement of ſo bold a Paſſion, remain'd for ſome time without anſwering and gave the Viſir to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the Entruſting him with ſuch a Secret had put him into a ſtrange Conſternation. Nevertheleſs, after he had conſider'd a while, and recovering himſelf of a ſuddain, Sir, ſaid he, the more dangerous the Tryal is upon which you put my Friendſhip, the more I am aſſur'd
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:95750:30"/>of yours. You are not ignorant to what a dreadful danger you expoſe me, but ſince we have begun, it behoves us to make an end. Should I go about to repair the Crime I am guilty of in the eye of the Sultan, I ſhould become an Offender in reſpect of my Friend, and yet not ceaſe to be the ſame in reſpect of my Soveraign. And therefore depend upon my Fidelity, as I depend upon your prudence.</p>
            <p>Upon thoſe words the Viſir embrac'd the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> and imparted to him his deſign to obtain <hi>Abra,</hi> by begging her of the Sultan. Ah, Sir, ſaid the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> would you ruin your ſelf and me too? The <hi>Sultans</hi> will ſooner part with their own Daughters, then the meaneſt ſlave in the <hi>Sarraglio;</hi> becauſe their Daughters are Burthens to 'em, which they would willingly be rid of, and for that by beſtowing 'em upon their weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Miniſters, they ſell 'em the Honour of that Alliance, or make uſe of it as a ſnare to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice 'em to their Avarice. But <hi>Mahomet,</hi> jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of every Woman that he keeps in his <hi>Serra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio,</hi> would look upon the Gift of one of his Woman, as a moſt ſenſible loſs, and therefore ſince <hi>Abra</hi> has an Affection for yee, and will not refuſe to correſpond'd with our Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we muſt ſeek which way to take ſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer methods. After this they propos'd to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſeveral intreagues, but came to no reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, only referring all things to time, to chance, and their own diligence, for the carrying on ſo nice an Enterprize, the <hi>Kiſler</hi> retir'd. But the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:95750:30"/>Viſir could not think of taking any repoſe till he had writ to his deareſt <hi>Abra;</hi> when at the very time that he was going about it, an Eunuch brought him a Billet, which after he had open'd it, he found to be <hi>Sarai</hi>'s Hand, who only wrote what her Miſtreſs dictated, and read the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lines.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>The Loyal One to the Onely One.</head>
                  <p>I know yee to be near me, and laden with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of Fortune; this might be ſufficient to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Tranſports of my Joy, did not my Love deſire ſomething elſe. When the diſtance of whole Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſeperated us, 'twas leſs cruel to me to endure your abſence, but the nearer you are, the more painful is it to me, to find my ſelf depriv'd of the pleaſure of your Preſence. I have heard no news of you: Ambition has robb'd my Love of one whole day: 'Tis too too long; but I expect yee, that I may ſeal your Pardon. <hi>Sarai,</hi> who better then my ſelf underſtands the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Heart, will give you an Account of it; and you will then find that you have no reaſon to complain, not ſo much as of one of all thoſe Minutes which I waſt remotely diſtant from you. If you love me, do ſomething that is impoſſible, to come and ſee the</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Loyal One.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the Viſir was over-joy'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the receipt of this Letter from <hi>Abra,</hi> yet was he no leſs perplex'd to find out a way to get into her Appartiment, but in regard he put his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:95750:31"/>whole confidence in the Addreſs and Friendſhip of the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> he flatter'd himſelf that he ſhould accompliſh his deſign; and with theſe hopes, he took his Pen, and return'd the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Anſwer, with which he entruſted the ſame Eunuch,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>THE Favors I have receiv'd from Fortune, have not prevail'd upon my Heart to loſe a moment of my wanted exactneſs in thinking upon you. They would have been more acceptable to me, if the load of troubleſom Affairs would have ſuffer'd me to ſatisfie the impatience of my Love. The Honour which the Sultan has conferr'd upon me, pleaſes me no otherwiſe then as it flatters my hopes. I have ſeen my Friend; there is nothing which I have not attempted to fullfill your Orders. Love me, think upon me, and live for my ſake, as for your ſake lives the</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Onely One.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But while <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Favour rais'd the Viſir to the higheſt pinacle of Fortune, and that <hi>Soliman</hi> met in <hi>Abra</hi>'s Conſtancy, with all that his Love could wiſh for from a Heart entirely devoted to him, Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> ſtill flatter'd himſelf that by <hi>Marama</hi>'s Intreagues he ſhould at length gain the heart of the young <hi>Muſcovite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which purpoſe that crafty Female-friend, having concerted with the Prince what Methods to take, liv'd with <hi>Abra</hi> under the greateſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection imaginable; and ever ſince the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview in her Cabinet, which had not the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:95750:31"/>which ſhe expected, ſhe obſerv'd her with a wonderful attention; and in regard ſhe had a peircing wit, and a ſmooth inſinuating way to dive into the moſt hidden Folds of the heart; ſhe perceiv'd that the young <hi>Muſcovite</hi> was not without ſome inward diſquiet, and rightly judg'd, that ſuch diſquiet could not proceed from any other occaſion then Love.</p>
            <p>Theſe Thoughts ſhe imputed to Prince <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and in regard Miſtruſt is inſeperable from Love, and that the twitches of Jealouſie do but ſerve to inflame a Heart the more, he found himſelf, by this Information, jealous without an Object, and more enamour'd then he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and in the midſt of theſe Agitations that inſpir'd his Jealouſie, he would needs put Pen to Paper, and accordingly wrote the following Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> to the Divine <hi>Abra.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE fear of offending yee, more powerful over my Heart, then that of loſing my Life, has hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd me from ſeeking any farther Opportunity to pay you a ſecond Viſit. You will not Love me, you ſay, but your Inſenſibility will not always oblige me not to Love you. I repeat it then, divine <hi>Abra,</hi> that I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore yee, but with a Paſſion ſo lively, and ſo violent, that 'tis impoſſible your Heart ſhould be inſenble of it, were it free from all other Engagement. If a Rival be the Obſtacle you meant, it ſhall not be ſo invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:95750:32"/>as you ſay it is, ſince there is no Love but what muſt give way to that, which he till death will have for yee, who writes himſelf</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Prince <hi>Soliman.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Marama</hi> undertook the delivery of this Letter, and judging well that <hi>Abra</hi> would refuſe to receive it from her hands, ſhe thought it the beſt way to call to her aſſiſtance Natural Curioſity. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe made her a viſit on purpoſe, and in the midſt of a world of pleaſant and divertiſing diſcourſe, having found a way to ſlide the Billet under <hi>Abra's</hi> Toylet, ſo ſoon as ſhe had done ſhe withdrew, and left her to her ſelf in hopes that the next day, by the effect of that Letter ſhe might read in her Countenance whether her heart were engag'd or no.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Viſir went to the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> and ſhew'd him <hi>Abra's</hi> Letter; and preſs'd him with ſo much earneſtneſs to procure him admittance in her Appartiment, of which he was the Abſolute Maſter, that at length in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of all the Hazar'd which the Eunuch ran, after he had conſider'd the moſt proper ways to put in Execution ſo perilous an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, ſeeing the Viſir had but little Beard, he carry'd him into his Cabinet, order'd him to rubb his face and hands with <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and putting him in an Eunuchs Habit, he feign'd to make a private Viſit in the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:95750:32"/>Appartiments, and to that purpoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all the Lamps in the Galleries to be put out, and with a Dark-Lanthorn accompany'd only with the Viſir in diſguize, he made as if he lookt into other Appartiments in his way, and at length chopt into <hi>Abra</hi>'s, who was juſt going to undreſs herſelf.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Abra</hi> might have ſome apprehenſion of the Truth, yet ſeeing the <hi>Kiſler</hi> with a black Eunuch enter at ſuch an unſeaſonable hour of the Night, her ſurprize not permitting her to recollect who the Black Eunuch ſhould be, ſhe thought at firſt that the Chief Miniſter of the Sultan's Pleaſures had been come by his Order to fetch her away, and expoſe her to his Paſſion; ſo that in the ſuddain Tumult which that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize had rais'd in her heart, of which ſhe was not then the Miſtreſs, ſhe ſwoonded away in <hi>Sarai</hi>'s Arms.</p>
            <p>They lay'd her upon the Bed; and the <hi>Kiſler</hi> commanding the reſt of the Slaves to quit the Room, went to work together with the Viſir to recover her out of her fainting fit, when <hi>Sarai,</hi> who held <hi>Abra</hi>'s Head, and took the Viſir for one of <hi>Kiſler</hi>'s Eunuchs, bid him fetch a Gold Bottle of Cordial water, that ſtood upon the Dreſſing Table; which the Viſir readily did, and at the ſame time ſeeing a Billet lying by the Bottle, ſlipt it into his Boſom. After this <hi>Abra</hi> recover'd her Spirits, and the <hi>Kiſler</hi> underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Reaſon of her ſwooning gave her to underſtand in two words how much ſhe was
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:95750:33"/>deceiv'd; and then diſcovering to her who the perſon was in a habit that ſo ill became him, he retir'd with <hi>Sarai,</hi> to the farther end of the Room, that the two Lovers might have the more liberty to entertain each other.</p>
            <p>How did they power forth their Hearts to one another! What Reciprocal Tenderneſſes! What Aſſurances of Fidelity! What Tortures of Minds to contrive which way to arrive at that happy Union which equally they Both deſir'd. At length after a thouſand Oaths and Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to love each other till death, and Meaſures taken to prevent her appearing at the Sultaneſſe's Feaſt, the <hi>Kiſler</hi> admoniſh'd 'em, that without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary danger they could not ſtay any longer.</p>
            <p>The Viſir delay'd as long as poſſibly he could the cruel moment of their Seperation, but at length taking both <hi>Abra</hi>'s hands, and fixing his Lips upon 'em he took his leave of her and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. The <hi>Kiſler</hi> carry'd him back to his Lodging, he quitted his Diſguiſe, embrac'd the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> and retir'd to his own Home.</p>
            <p>But under what a ſtrange ſurprize was the aſtoniſh'd Lover, when opening the Billet which he found upon <hi>Abra</hi>'s Toylet, he found that it came from Prince <hi>Soliman;</hi> that he was not only in love with <hi>Abra,</hi> but that he had ſeen her, that he had wrought himſelf into ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence with her as to ſend her Letters, and that which ſeem'd more Cruel to him was, that <hi>Abra</hi> had told him no thing of it; ſo that her Silence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:95750:33"/>to him a Myſtery that created in him a moſt furious Jealouſy.</p>
            <p>He read the Letter over and over again, and tho' it plainly ſhew'd him that <hi>Abra</hi> had never Correſponded with his Rival's Paſſion, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, in regard the Prince had an outward Merit which was taking, that it was certain he had ſeen her, he attributed that which was only an effect of prudence to the wavering of a ſhaken Heart.</p>
            <p>Is this, ſaid he, in a terrible Agony of mind, is this the fidelity which the Ingrateful has ſworn to me with ſo many Oaths! If her heart be ſo impenetrable to the Paſſion of this Prince, why did ſhe not let me know it! At thoſe words, whatever the fury of jealouſy could ſuggeſt to a miſtruſtful Love, and which believ'd it ſelf to be offended crouded into his thoughts: And he was about to have ruin'd his Rival by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing his attempt to the Sultan. But beſides that it was his Intereſt to conceal <hi>Abra</hi> from him, he had a heart too Great and Generous to do any thing that was baſe and treacherous. To Impart it to the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> was to create a moſt terrible Confuſion in the Serraglio, and in all the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family; and to diſſemble his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment with <hi>Abra,</hi> was to favour the Projects and Contrivances of his Rival; to make known his jealouſy to her, was to charge her with a piece of Infidelity of which perhaps ſhe might not be guilty; and to accuſe himſelf of a Curioſity, no no leſs indiſcreet then Inconſiderate. At laſt all
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:95750:34"/>theſe Irreſolutions ended in ſending to the <hi>Kiſler</hi> to let <hi>Sarai</hi> have the Liberiy to wait upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marama,</hi> who had a vigilant eye upon every thing that paſt in the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> Appartiment, knew that the <hi>Kiſler</hi> had been there, and not doubting but it was to prepare her to ſee the Sultan, ſhe was alarum'd for the Princes ſake, and reſtleſs to know the fate of her Billet ſhe went the next morning to <hi>Abra</hi>'s Appartiment. At what time the ſecret which ſhe imparted to her of the <hi>Kiſler</hi>'s Viſit, confirm'd her the more in her firſt Conjectures; and for her better ſatisfaction, ſhe cunningly dropt into a diſcourſe about Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> but finding that <hi>Abra</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd her no Anſwer, by which ſhe could ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that ſhe had ever ſeen his Letter, ſhe preſently began to think, that it might have lit into the <hi>Kiſler</hi>'s hands.</p>
            <p>The Dread of this, conſtrain'd her to open her mind to <hi>Abra,</hi> and frankly to ask her whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe had ſeen what <hi>Soliman</hi> had wrote to her. <hi>Abra,</hi> ſurpriz'd, and falling into the ſame Dread, bluſh'd and lookt pale, both at the ſame time; and having aſſur'd <hi>Marama</hi> that ſhe never ſaw any thing, the Billet was ſought for up and down to no purpoſe, ſo that the Prince's Wittie Procureſs being quite overcome with her feares and Grief could not refrain from ſending forth a loud Cry, and looking upon <hi>Abra</hi> with an Eye of Conſternation, Ah, Madam ſaid ſhe, Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> is ſacrific'd to <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s fury, the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:95750:34"/>
               <hi>Kiſler,</hi> of whom you ſay not a word to me, and who came that night to your Apparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prepare you for the Paſſion of his Maſter, has the Letter without doubt, if you conceal your ſelf from my Syncerity, you are agreed with the Sultan, and <hi>Soliman</hi> is ruin'd; but if the <hi>Kiſler</hi> has got the Letter, and you know nothing of it, you are alſo ruin'd as well as the Prince.</p>
            <p>You do me wrong, ſaid <hi>Abra,</hi> I am not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of betraying the Prince, ſince you know that my ſilence bury'd the dangerous attempt he made to ſee me. As for the <hi>Kiſler</hi>'s viſit, It hought my ſelf not bound to give any Body an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it; I have no Correſpondence with the Sultan; and therefore if I am ruin'd, and the Prince too, by the ſurprize of his Letter, he muſt impute it to the imprudence of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ventur'd it. But let happen what will, you will do me a kindneſs, to diſſwade the Prince to deſiſt the putting of me to any farther trouble to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra</hi> and <hi>Marama</hi> were under equal Agitatinos of mind, but the one and the other being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the Letter had lit into the <hi>Kiſler</hi>'s hands, they expected ſome terrible diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der about it. The reſt of their Diſcourſe was no way divertizing; and the Paſſion ſhe ſaw <hi>Abra</hi> in, beſides thoſe other Anxieties that were plainly perceptible in her Viſage, caus'd the other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to imagin, that ſince the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi</hi>'s Viſit was not upon the Sultan's Accompt, he was
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:95750:35"/>ſetting ſome other Important Engin of Love at Work, which render'd <hi>Abra</hi> ſo inacceſſible to the Prince.</p>
            <p>She retir'd therefore, but with a Reſolution to watch all <hi>Abra</hi>'s Motions ſo narrowly, that it ſhould be impoſſible for her not to diſcover the Correſpondence. <hi>Abra,</hi> on the other ſide, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing call'd <hi>Sarai</hi> to her, gave her a full accompt of all her grievances; ſhe inform'd her of Prince <hi>Soliman's</hi> Paſſion which her prudence had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd from her, and lay'd open to her her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet for the loſs of the Billet. But at the ſame time that theſe diſcourſes put 'em into moſt dreadful Agonies, their terrours were yet more augmented by the Arrival of a Black Eunuch, who brought <hi>Sarai</hi> an Order from the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> to attend him at his Appartiment.</p>
            <p>This was only to ſend her privately to the Viſir, who ſtay'd for her, and no ſooner ſaw her, but caſting a look full of Fire and Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon her; Very well <hi>Sarai,</hi> ſaid he, you are then in a confederacy with <hi>Abra</hi> to betray me. Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> is in Love with her, he Viſits her, he writes to her, and you from whom I expect an Account of all theſe things, you ſee me at her Appartiment, and conceal this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity from me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sarai</hi> anſwer'd the Viſir with all the prudence and Modeſty that ſuch a nice Juſtification re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd: But when <hi>Sarai,</hi> going about to clear <hi>Abra,</hi> aſſur'd him, that our of her ſingular diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, ſhe never had made known to her the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:95750:35"/>of Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> till ſhe came to be diſturb'd for the loſs of the Billet. How! cruel <hi>Sarai,</hi> ſaid the Viſir, what is that thou tell'ſt me? Did <hi>Abra</hi> conceal from thee the Prince's love? Had not that Love made ſome Impreſſion in her heart, would ſhe have ever conceal'd it from thee? <hi>Abra</hi> does not yet perhaps correſpond with the Prince's Affection, but who can aſſure me ſhe will not yield at laſt, ſince ſhe is ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to carry it on at the beginning; who ſhall aſſure me that her heart does not already begin to waver, ſince her Silence tells my jealouſy what ever I can prognoſticate of moſt Funeſt and fatal to me?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sarai</hi> leſt nothing omitted that lay in her pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to calm a mind that ſhe ſaw turmoyl'd with all that the moſt reſtleſs Suſpitions, and the moſt piercing Pains have in 'em of tumultuous and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous. However 'twas impoſſible, upon the firſt ſight, to reduce him to a perfect Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility. Nevertheleſs ſhe left him in a Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo as to wiſh that he might be abſolutely convinc'd of <hi>Abra</hi>'s Innocence: He told her, 'twas he himſelf who had lit upon the Letter, that the <hi>Kiſler</hi> knew nothing of it; and that he was ſo generous, that tho' he were betray'd, he would not for the ſatisfaction of his Revenge, make a baſe and treacherous uſe of what his Curioſity, perhaps too Indiſcreet, had put into his hands.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:95750:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra</hi> was under Mortal fears, when <hi>Sarai</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd and came to give her an Accompt of what the Viſir had ſaid. But ſhe was almoſt at her wits end that he had lit upon <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Letter. So that whatever danger would have befallen the Prince or Her, had the <hi>Kiſler</hi> found the Letter, ſhe would have been more contented rather to have periſh'd, then to have given her Lover any Ground for thoſe Suſpitions he had of her.</p>
            <p>Her Grief and Vexation for this Accident caus'd ſuch a Commotion in her Veins, as caſt her into a Violent fever; ſo that ſhe took her Bed, nor would ſhe ſuffer <hi>Sarai</hi> to ſtirr from the Bed ſide, to the end ſhe might be ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of her Pains, by ſharing with her in her Tears.</p>
            <p>In the mean time night was come; and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rama</hi> with a wonderful Exactneſs had a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eye upon every thing that paſs'd in the <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covites</hi> Appartiment, and in regar'd ſhe durſt not confide in any Body but herſelf, but yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded all diſcovery, ſhe took the Habit of one of her Slaves, and ſat upon a Bench not above two or three Paces from <hi>Abra</hi>'s Door.</p>
            <p>The Lamps were not as yet lighted in the Galleries of the Serraglio, and it began already to be ſo dark, that there was no diſtinguiſhing colours, when ſhe ſaw an Eunuch, who ſtopping about ten paces from her, clapt with one of his hands upon the other. <hi>Marama,</hi> who made no queſtion but this was ſome concerted Signal,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:95750:36"/>did the ſame; and at the ſame time the Eunuch coming up to her, Who's there, ſaid he, <hi>Sohema?</hi> Yes, ſaid <hi>Marama.</hi> Here then, reply'd the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, carry this Letter to <hi>Sarai,</hi> and at the ſame time putting the Billet into her Hands, he vaniſh'd. On the other ſide, <hi>Marama</hi> return'd to her Appartiment, and opening the Letter read the following lines.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>The Onely One to the Faithleſs One</head>
                  <p>COuld I have thought it poſſible that I ſhould ever have given you this Name! The more I ſeek for Terms proper to Expreſs the Exceſs of my Grief, the fewer can I meet with; and the more I deſire to excuſe the Infidelity, the leſs I find you Innocent. 'Tis not the Quality of my Rival that terrifies me, 'tis the little aſſurance I have of your heart, ſince you have ſeen Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> and that you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd from me, Your Love, your Interview, and his Letter. You will be offended perhaps at my preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in taking it off your Toylet, but all things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for a Love ſo violent and jealous as mine. Would to God you were as Innocent as <hi>Sarai</hi> would make me believe. She will give yee an Accompt of my diſcretion, and thence you may judge, that what ever wounds you give my heart, I ſhall never ceaſe to love yee.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Marama</hi> did not know the Viſir's hand; but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering by the Letter, that <hi>Abra</hi> was in Love, and that ſhe was belov'd, and that that ſame Lover had been introduc'd into her Appartiment
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:95750:37"/>by the <hi>Kiſler</hi> himſelf, ſhe rightly judg'd that it muſt needs be a perſon of the Higheſt Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>She could not inform Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening of an Adventure that ſo nearly concern'd him; but the next Morning ſhe fail'd not to be with him. But it was a double Aſtoniſhment to him to underſtand that he had a Rival, whoſe Credit extended ſo far as to give him Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the Serraglio; and that it was in the power of that Rival, having his Letter, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the Sultan to his Ruin.</p>
            <p>A thouſand different thoughts preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves all at once to his mind; but none but onely ſuch as appear'd no leſs Terrible to threaten his Life then his Love. He knew not the Viſir's hand, but <hi>Muſtapha Cuproli,</hi> who arriv'd about two days before from <hi>Chio,</hi> of which Iſland, and of the reſt of the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> he was <hi>Baſha,</hi> being come to pay him a Viſir, He ſhew'd him ſome lines of the Letter, and ask'd him whether he knew the Hand. As well as my own, reply'd <hi>Cuproli,</hi> 'tis the Viſir <hi>Soliman</hi>'s: Nor Can any Body know it better, becauſe he was <hi>Kiaia</hi> to my Brother <hi>Cuproli Oglou,</hi> when he was Viſir; and for that at that time I had great Correſpondencies with him.</p>
            <p>The Knowledge of his Rival's Quality re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled Prince <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Vexation, and his Grief with all. <hi>Cuproli</hi> was Witty, Ambitious, Bold Intreaguing, Undaunted, a great Captain, and <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Intimate Friend. He had marry'd
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:95750:37"/>his Siſter to <hi>Siaous Baſha,</hi> General of the <hi>Spahi</hi>'s; and in regard that <hi>Cuproli</hi> had been the Son and Brother of two Viſirs, nothing could beat it out of his Head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that that ſame preferment was due to him; nor was there any one who was advanc'd to that Dignity, but he became his Mortal Enemy at the ſame time, and whoſe downfal he did not wiſh in hopes of having his Turn.</p>
            <p>Theſe Ambitious thoughts he never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd from <hi>Soliman,</hi> and the Prince was ſo far from condemning 'em, that he flatter'd 'em, and aſſiſted him under hand, in hopes that if <hi>Cuproli</hi> ſhould obtain the Chief Miniſtry of the Empire, he might prove a favourable Support to his Affairs.</p>
            <p>With a mind thus diſpos'd and inflam'd with jealouſy againſt the Grand Viſir, he carry'd <hi>Cuproli</hi> into his Cloſet, and ſhutting himſelf up alone with him, Do you love me ſo well <hi>Cuproli,</hi> ſaid He, as that I may relye upon your Fidelity? There is nothing, anſwer'd <hi>Cuproli,</hi> that I would not undertake, to aſſure yee that I am leſs my own then I am yours. The Sultan has made choice of a Viſir, reply'd the Prince, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour only has exalted <hi>Baſha Soliman</hi> to a Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which is your Due; he is the moſt Intimate of my Brother's Favourites; but he hates me, and my life is not ſafe ſo long as he Governs the Empire; we muſt find out a way to ruin him in the good Opinion of the Sultan, and that the Dignity wherewith he has honour'd him,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:95750:38"/>may prove as fatal to him, as to thoſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded him. Unite you Friends, and <hi>Siaous</hi>'s, to the end they may concurr in a Deſign, which will ſecure me from a Death which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I certainly foreſee, and which will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the Obſtacle to the Fortune you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
            <p>What you ſay, reply'd <hi>Cuproli,</hi> is conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Inclinations of my heart; but 'tis no eaſy thing to bring this Enterprize to paſs: nor is there any way to ſucceed in it, but by Contrivances manag'd at a diſtance. So ſoon as I have ſounded <hi>Siaous,</hi> Ile give ye an Accompt what Courſe is to be follow'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> thought it ſufficient to incenſe <hi>Cupro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li</hi> with the conſideration of his fortune, and the concern he had for the Life of a Prince his friend; and that there was no need of impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to him the ſecret of his Amour, which would have only ſerv'd to have render'd his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals more ſuſpected, as proceeding more from Intereſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cuproli</hi> conferr'd with <hi>Siaous,</hi> and they both concluded, that 'twas not poſſible directly to attack the Viſir by any open Attempts, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him from the Grand Seignior's Affection; for he lov'd him too well, and therefore that would be to ruin themſelves; but that it behov'd 'em ſo to order it, during the whole Campaign, as to fruſtrate all his Deſigns, and to render all his Undertakings ſo ſucceſsleſs, that his Misfortunes might work him into Diſgrace.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:95750:38"/>That every thing ſeem'd to favour 'em in this Contrivance, ſeeing the Viſir had propos'd <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proli</hi> to Command the Armies in <hi>Hungary;</hi> for which reaſon it was that <hi>Mahomet</hi> had ſent for him from <hi>Chio;</hi> and that for his part he could not be diſpens'd with, becauſe he Commanded all the <hi>Spahi</hi>'s, which render'd him abſolute Arbitrator of the ſucceſs of all ſuch Battels as ſhould happen to be fought.</p>
            <p>Things being thus reſolv'd between <hi>Siaous</hi> and <hi>Cuproli,</hi> and the time for entring into the Field approaching, the Sultan haſten'd, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed anticipated the Departure of the Viſir, and oblig'd him to be with all ſpeed at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> that he might iſſue forth all requiſite Orders for drawing the Army together.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Fever that ſeiz'd <hi>Abra</hi> prov'd to be of long continuance and danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The Viſir alſo, not having receiv'd any Anſwer of the Letter which he had written, began more and more to ſuſpect the worſt: He was therefore deſirous to be better ſatisfy'd by <hi>Sarai,</hi> who inform'd him, that never any ſuch Billet was brought to <hi>Abra</hi>'s Appartiment. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the Eunuch was ſent for, who affirm'd that he gave it to <hi>Sohema;</hi> but <hi>Sohema</hi> denying the matter, it was judg'd that the Letter had been intercepted, and <hi>Sarai</hi> charg'd <hi>Marama</hi> with the Treachery. But becauſe the Viſir would not that the <hi>Kiſler</hi> ſhould be inform'd of <hi>Soliman</hi>'s being in Love with <hi>Abra,</hi> for fear it ſhould come to the Sultan<hi>'s</hi> Ear, he thought it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:95750:39"/>to obtain that Favour from the Maſter of the Eunuchs, that <hi>Marama</hi> ſhould be remov'd to an Appartiment out of the way.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kiſler</hi> alſo did him the kindneſs to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce him a ſecond time into <hi>Abra</hi>'s chamber diſguis'd in a Phyſician's habit, to the end he might obtain his ſatisfaction from her ſelf; which abſolutely diſſipated all his Jealouſies, and which much more conduc'd to the Recovery of her Health, then if he had been a real Artiſt.</p>
            <p>'Twas the next day after he had receiv'd this Satisfaction that the Sultan Commanded him to depart for <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and to draw together the moſt powerful Army that poſſibly he could to oppoſe the Enemies Deſigns and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as Fame had given it out, to beſiege <hi>Buda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis well known that the Viſir did all he could to perſwade the Sultan to go in Perſon into <hi>Hungary,</hi> and take upon him the Command of the Army; inſomuch that 'twas the wonder of the whole Port, that he ſhould deſire the preſence of a Perſon, who would but leſſen and ecclipſe his Power. But it was the effect of Jealouſy and his fear, leaſt <hi>Mahomet,</hi> during his Abſence, ſhould happen to caſt his Eyes upon <hi>Abra,</hi> the Conſequences of which might prove fatal to his Love. Whereas the Sultan carrying his Brothers along with him, it would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd him from that diſquiet which Prince <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Paſſion caus'd within him.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:95750:39"/>
            <p>But <hi>Mahomet</hi> thought it not convenient to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard his Perſon, conſidering the Condition of his Affairs. So that the Viſir being oblig'd to a haſty departure, could not have the pleaſure of bidding his dear <hi>Muſcovite</hi> farewel, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inſtead of taking his perſonal leave, he was forc'd to content himſelf with writing the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Letter to pay her that Homage.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>SOLIMAN Viſir <hi>to his Dear</hi> ABRA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> Haſty Order forces my Departure, and I am going to endeavour to render my ſelf as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your Eſteem, as I am perſwaded of your Love. How tedious does this Campaign ſeem to me already, and with what Unwillingneſs ſhould I act, did I not know that you would Love me leſs, if I had leſs a Love for Honour: If you keep your word, no Rival will be the better for my Abſence. Afford me the Conſolation of frequent underſtanding the Condition of your Heart, and be aſſur'd, that nothing ſhall ever abate the Love of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Soliman Viſir.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:95750:40"/>
            <p>The care for the ſafe delivery of this Letter, was the laſt which he took at <hi>Adrianople;</hi> and being thus departed in order perform his Duty, within a few days after the Sultan remov'd to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> with his two Brothers, and all the Train of his Serraglio.</p>
            <trailer>The End of the Firſt Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:95750:40"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Abra-Mulè:</hi> OR, THE HISTORY Of the Depoſition of <hi>MAHOMET</hi> IV. EMPEROR of the TURKS.</head>
            <head>The Second Part.</head>
            <p>THE Vizir march'd long marches directly to <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and the farther his Marches remov'd him from her, the more he felt his heart oppreſs'd with the burthen of his ſighs. What ever Confidence he had in the Aſſurances that <hi>Abra</hi> had giv'n him of an invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:95750:41"/>Fidelity, Prince <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Love gall'd him, and the great difficulty always to conceal that Beauty from the Sultan's Eyes made his Love tremble.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> whoſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was no leſs violent then unfortunate, found himſelf o're whelm'd with an infinite number of threatning Difficulties: He ſaw that <hi>Abra</hi>'s heart was no way touch'd with his Love, that it was prepoſſeſs'd with the Merits of a belov'd Rival; that this Rival was in great Power, and the Favourite of a diſtruſtful Brother, and that the <hi>Kiſler</hi> was deep in his Intreague, that <hi>Mara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> was become ſuſpected, and for that reaſon all acceſs to the fair <hi>Muſcovite</hi> was forbid her; that the Reſolutions of <hi>Siaous</hi> and <hi>Cuproli</hi> would perhaps become uſeleſs to him through the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſness of Execution, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> might fall in Love with <hi>Abra,</hi> and in the midſt of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions he ſaw nothing but grounds of Fear and Diſpair.</p>
            <p>'Twas at the beginning of <hi>May</hi> that <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> with all his Court, arriv'd within ſight of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> The weather was the moſt love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the world, and the <hi>Boſtangi Baſha</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken care to dreſs up the pleaſant Gardens of the Serraglio, and ſet 'em out with all the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Politeneſs that their Maſter could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            <p>The Proſpect of theſe Gardens is wonderful to thoſe that come to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> by Water; more eſpecially that ſame admirable Terrafs,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:95750:41"/>which <hi>Achmet</hi> caus'd to be rais'd for a Walk for the Sultaneſſes, and which ſurpaſſes all the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence that can be imagin'd enchanting the Eyes with the ſight of it. To devertiſe himſelf with ſo delicious a Proſpect, <hi>Mahomet</hi> having lain by the Sea ſide about three Leagues from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> embark'd together with the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſs <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> in a light Saique, magnificently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn'd, and ſteer'd by the <hi>Boſtangi Baſha.</hi> The reſt of the Women, and Perſons belonging to the Court, were diſtributed into ſmaller, but very neat Barges. And thus the floating and magnificent Court row'd toward the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which is form'd by a little Bay, made in the likeneſs of a Canal, at the foot of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio.</p>
            <p>They were juſt entring into it, when a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Tempeſt riſing of a ſuddain caus'd ſo great a Diſorder among the Barges, and made ſuch a confuſion, that there was no longer any Order to be obſerv'd. The Sultan's Bark put in firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſet him a ſhoar, while the reſt confuſedly croud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together fell foul one upon another, and one of them which carry'd the Women had the misfortune to over-ſet. As for the Seamen they took care for no Body but themſelves, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Women to periſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when Prince <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who was in the next Bark to that which had miſcarried, not only encourag'd the Seamen with large promiſes of Reward, to ſuccour the poor Women in diſtreſs, but to enliven 'em by his Example, threw himſelf into the Water and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:95750:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:95750:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:95750:43"/>luckily took one by the Hair, as ſhe was juſt going to ſink, and recovering his own Bark, by the help of his ſlaves, got her out of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>The Diſorder which this unexpected Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent had caus'd, the motion of the Waves, the darkneſs of the gloomy Weather, would not permit the Prince to know at firſt the Perſon to whom he had lent his Aſſiſtance. But how ſtrangely aſtoniſh'd, How over-joy'd! when he underſtood, that but for him the fair <hi>Abra</hi> had been ſwallow'd up by the mercileſs Waves. She was fallen into a Swoond, and whatever they could do, ſhe did not recover her Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses till the Prince was landed, and had got her aſhoar.</p>
            <p>Then it was that ſhe open'd her Eyes, and calling to mind what had befallen her, her firſt care was to ask for her dear <hi>Sarai:</hi> The Seamen had had the good luck to ſave her, and the greateſt part of the reſt; but <hi>Sarai</hi> who thought <hi>Abra</hi> loſt, was fall'n into fainting Fits, from which ſhe could not recover: However there was a neceſſity of carrying her to her Miſtreſs let her Condition be what it would, in regard that nothing but her own Eyes could aſſure her of the Life of ſo dear a Confident. It would have been Imprudence for <hi>Soliman</hi> to have troubl'd her with his Love, conſidering the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction ſhe was in, and therefore he thought it ſufficient not to quit her till he had caus'd her, together with <hi>Sarai,</hi> to be carry'd into one of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:95750:43"/>the <hi>Boſtangi</hi>'s Lodgings, which was oppoſite to the neareſt Gate; from whence the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> who was inform'd of the Accident, took care to have her remov'd to the Appartiment which he had appointed for her.</p>
            <p>This Adventure, which one would have thought ſhould have been favourable to <hi>Soliman</hi> begate him new Vexations, becauſe that what ever care the <hi>Kiſler</hi> took to ſtifle the noiſe of it, the <hi>Boſtangi,</hi> to whoſe Lodging ſhe was firſt brought, inform'd the <hi>Boſtangi Bachi,</hi> and gave him a wonderful deſcription of the <hi>Muſcovite's</hi> Beauty, whoſe Name the Sultan bad hardly heard of, that that ſame great Officer, who was deeply concern'd in his Maſter's pleaſures, was not only contented to give him a Relation of the Accident, but aggravated with ſo much Vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency what he had heard, that the Sultan the ſame Evening demanded an Account of her from the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Eunuch, who ſaw himſelf upon the brink of the fatal Moment which he had always dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and who kept himſelf prepar'd for all Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, anſwer'd the Sultan, without leſſening or magnifying the Sultan's beauty, that ſhe kept her Bed, in ſo weak a Condition, and brought ſo low, by the Terrour of the Affright into which the danger ſhe had eſcap'd had caſt her, that he knew not whether ſhe would live or no; that nothing but Reſt for ſome time could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her, and that ſo ſoon as ſhe ſhould be in a Condition to enjoy the Honour of appearing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:95750:44"/>before his Highneſs, he would not fail to come and receive his Orders, and yeild him Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The Sultan being ſatisfied with the <hi>Kiſler</hi>'s Anſwer, commanded him to take particular care of her, added two thouſand Aſpers a day to her former Allowance, and Order'd his chief Phyſican <hi>Sedekias,</hi> a Jew, to viſit her, and give him an Account of her.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kisler Agaſi</hi> having warded off this firſt Blow had the leiſure to ſee <hi>Abra,</hi> as he did forthwith, under pretence to give her notice of the Sultan's Generoſity, but indeed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult together what Methods were requiſite to make her ſelf appear to <hi>Sedekias</hi> more ſick then ſhe was, and to drill out a counterfeit Diſtemper, till they could think of ſome other Intreague to fend off ſhe Blow: And in the mean time he wrote to the Viſir, and gave him a full Account of the Accident, with all its Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>'Twas no hard matter to amuſe the Sultan for above a Month, and till he receiv'd the News, that the Siege of <hi>Buda</hi> was fully reſolv'd upon in a Council of War which the Emperor held at <hi>Neuſtadt,</hi> and that Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> were upon their march at the head of Fourſcore Thouſand Men, in order to ſit down before the place: That the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Town, who was a reſolute Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado, had already burnt <hi>Peſt,</hi> that he might have nothing elſe to do, but to mind the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Buda,</hi> and that there was nothing want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a vigorous reſiſtance.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:95750:44"/>
            <p>The Emperor's Attempt upon that Place, which bad prov'd unſucceſsful two Years before, the new Fortifications of the Town, the numerous Garriſon, the vaſt Stores of Ammunition and Proviſion, and the Confidence he had in the Valour of Viſir <hi>Soliman,</hi> who was able to draw together above a hundred Thouſand Men to relieve it; all theſe things were great Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to ſet the Sultan's Heart at reſt, and made him give himſelf up to his Pleaſures with as much ſecurity, as if he had been repoſing in the Arms of a profound Peace. Therefore in regard he daily preſs'd the <hi>Kisler</hi> to haſten the the pleaſure which be expected from the <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covite,</hi> and it being impoſſible any longer to fain a continuation of the Sickneſs, the Eunuch, who found he could no longer delay the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting her before the Sultan, thought it high time to awaken the Jealouſy of the Sultaneſs <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> ſo that ſhe being privately made acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Diverſion that was preparing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt her Pleaſures, all Engins might be ſet at work to thwart, the new Deſires that now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd the luſtful <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Soliman,</hi> who flatter'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that ſo conſiderable a piece of Service as he had done the <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> deſerv'd a favourable Acknowledgment of his Love, burn'd with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience to give her a Viſit: But the familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which <hi>Marama</hi> had with her was broken off, and all that ſhe could learn by means of her Slaves was this, that a long Ague had atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:95750:45"/>the Accident that befell her, and that ſhe kept her Bed very much, ſo that there was no coming at her, and all that the crafty Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs could agitate by her Artifices was to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt one of <hi>Abra</hi>'s ſlaves, and engage her to ſlide a Letter into her Miſtreſſes hands, yet ſo as that ſhe ſhould not diſcover by what hand it came. This <hi>Marama</hi> make known to <hi>Soliman,</hi> who unwilling to loſe the Opportunity, put Pen to Paper, and gave the Billet to his Confident.</p>
            <p>The Slave whom ſhe had won, and well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, diſcharged her Truſt with ſo much dexterity, that <hi>Abra</hi> found the Billet in her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, not knowing who had been ſo bold as to put it there, and not able to withſtand her Curioſity, ſhe open'd it, and read the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lines.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:95750:45"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Abra.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> Lover whoſe Happineſs it was to wreſt you from the Jaws of Death, labours under moſt mortal diſquiets, becauſe he can hear nothing of a life more precious to him them his own. What fatal deſtiny ſo orders it, Divine <hi>Abra,</hi> that you are as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible to my Eyes, as your heart is impenetrable to my Love. How happy is the <hi>Viſir,</hi> Madam, and how do I envy the good Fortune of my Rival! He enjoys you, though never ſo remote, while I am only near you, to feel with ſo much the more grief the weight of your inſenſibility. Nevertheleſs, I adore yee, as little Compaſſion as you have upon the Pains which you cauſe me to ſuffer; and how ſevere ſoever you are, you only ſhall poſſeſs a Heart which will ever be at your Devotion, while lives<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Prince Soliman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra</hi> ow'd her life to the Prince, and nothing griev'd her more then that ſhe was beholding to him; ſeeing that her heart being abſolutely the Viſir's, ſhe could not pay to his Rival all that acknowledgment which he expected for ſo great a piece a Service. Her acknowledgment
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:95750:46"/>therefore went no farther, then only to pitty him for throwing away his Affection upon an object that could not admit it. But after ſhe had read a ſecond time that part of the Letter which gave her to underſtand that the Viſirs being in love with her, was not unknown to the Prince, it ſtruck her with a more then extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Grief; and not doubting but it was the letter which had been intercepted in the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, the conſideration of that infus'd into her a Deteſtation of ſuch a paltry Trick, and that Deteſtation of the fact, ſoon turn'd to a hatred of the Perſon; for that being perſwaded that ſince the Viſir and he both knew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Rivals, they could not but hate each other, her heart never waver'd which ſide to take. So that <hi>Seliman</hi>'s Billet was ſo far from moving <hi>Abra</hi>'s heart, that it did but inſpire her with hatred, tell then ſhe never had for the Prince, and that ſhe might not undergoe the ſame Reproaches which the Viſir had made her upon her firſt ſilence, the firſt time ſhe wrote ſhe ſacrific'd to his view this Letter from her Rival.</p>
            <p>This was the Poſture of Affairs at <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> while other intreagues were in Agitation at <hi>Belgrade. Siaous</hi> and <hi>Cuproli Baſha</hi>'s, who were the moſt ſignaliz'd for their Valour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, had as I have already ſaid, devoted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſerve Prince <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Paſſion by the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of the Viſir. Finding therefore that <hi>Buda</hi> was beſeig'd, and that the Viſir had given out Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:95750:46"/>for the drawing together a numerous Army, with a deſign to relieve the place, they reſolv'd by all manner of Artifices to prevent the ſuccour of it, and rather ſo to order it that the Viſir ſhould loſe a Battel, then have the Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of ſaving it; not queſtioning but a loſs of that importance would be attended with the Downfall, and perhaps the Death of that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Nevertheleſs the better to conceal their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, and not to endanger both their Heads, at one time, in the hazards which this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy might produce, they thought it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient that <hi>Siaous,</hi> who had a great Reputation among the Soldiers ſhould remain in the Army, and that <hi>Cuproli,</hi> who had accepted the command of the <hi>Dardanells,</hi> which is an Employment of great Truſt, ſhould keep his poſt there, where he might ſo much the more effectually make uſe of his power to detain or divert the Succor and Subſiſtance of the Armies. On the other ſide, Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> being deſirous to take all the precautions imaginable that might conduce toward the ſucceſs of his Enterprize, thought it convenient that <hi>Michael Abaffi,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> ſhould be conſtrain'd to declare himſelf for the Emperor, to the end the <hi>Turks</hi> might be depriv'd of the ſubſiſtances which they drew from him as their Tributary; and to the end, that at the ſame time they might act in the Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> and by keeping <hi>Tecekly</hi> in play, prevent his joining the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:95750:47"/>
            <p>The Viſir, who forſaw the conſequence of theſe two deſigns, did two things in hopes to diſappoint 'em. In the firſt place he order'd <hi>Sultan Galga</hi> and the <hi>Baſha,</hi> with all ſpeed to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite their forces with <hi>Takeli's,</hi> in order to make a powerful diverſion in the Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> and at the ſame time to defend the Paſſes of <hi>Tranſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Siaous</hi> began the Execution of his Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy with his thwarting the prudent contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of the Viſir, and having at the ſame time engag'd the <hi>Baſha</hi> of <hi>Walachia</hi> in his intreague, 'twas no hard matter for the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> to beat the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Troops that ſhew'd themſelves upon the frontiers of <hi>Tranſilvania.</hi> They made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves maſters of <hi>Hermansbourg,</hi> forc'd <hi>Abaffi</hi> to break with the <hi>Turks,</hi> and reinforc'd with his Troops, fell upon the <hi>Tartars,</hi> forſaken by the <hi>Baſha</hi> of <hi>Walachia,</hi> ſo that by this firſt blow of <hi>Siaous</hi>'s intreaguing Treachery, the Viſir found himſelf at the beginning of the Campaign de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of that ſubſiſtance he was wont to have out of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> and upon which he rely'd; and at the ſame time bereft of that Advantage which he expected from his projected Diverſion in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Charles</hi> lay'd Siege to <hi>Buda</hi> with Forty Thouſand Foot, and Twenty Thouſand Horſe, Sixty great Pieces of Cannon, and forty Mortars; and <hi>Abdi Baſha,</hi> the Renegado, left nothing omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that a prudent, undaunted, and accompliſh'd Governour could do for the preſervation of a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:95750:47"/>place that was furniſh with a Garriſon of Ten Thouſand Men, and all things neceſſary for a long defence.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, the Trenches and Attacks were carry'd on with all the Vigour and all the Art imaginable; the Sallies were frequent and terrible, and it coſt the <hi>Germans</hi> a world of Blood, before they got to the body of the place.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Grand Viſir gave out Orders every way for the rendevouzing an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſufficient to raiſe the Siege, and manger all the ſecret Obſtacles that he met with, but of which he knew not the reaſon, having muſter'd together an Army which he thought ſufficient to decide the fortune of <hi>Buda</hi> by a Battle, he croſs'd the <hi>Theyſſe.</hi> But they ſtill founder'd his purpoſes with ſo many new oppoſitions, that he was no ſooner got over the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> towards the end of <hi>July,</hi> but <hi>Buda,</hi> after a cloſe Siege of ſix weeks, began to be very much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſt.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs he ſurmounted all theſe difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and about the beginning of <hi>Auguſt</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd within five Leagues of the Lines, and encamp'd upon the riſing Grounds adjoining to the <hi>Danaw.</hi> Now in regard that <hi>Abdi Boſha</hi> had ſent intelligence, that his frequent Sallies had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly weaken'd his Garriſon, and promis'd him to hold out all the reſt of the Campaign, provided he might be reinforc'd with freſh ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of Men, the Viſir commanded the <hi>Seraskier</hi> to force his way, and put in a Relief of two Thouſand <hi>Janiſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:95750:48"/>
            <p>To this purpoſe the <hi>Seraskier</hi> ſet forward with ſix Thouſand Foot and three Thouſand <hi>Spahi</hi>'s, which made up a body to defend the two Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Janiſaries.</hi> Their intention was to force the <hi>Imperialiſt's</hi> Quarter, while <hi>Adbi</hi> made a Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> and by that means to throw in two Thouſand men into the Town. But <hi>Siaous</hi> having found a way, by means of a Deſerter, to inform Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of all theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, he ſent forth a numerous Body to meet the Enemy without the Lines. The Combat was ſmart and cruel; the number of the ſlain on both ſides was very great; the <hi>Turks</hi> no ſooner broken, but rally'd again, perhaps they would have forc'd their paſſage, if the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi</hi>'s, whoſe Officers obſerv'd the private moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Siaous,</hi> had not forſaken the <hi>Janiſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> ſo that the Infantry being left alone and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacqn'd on every ſide, could no longer defend themſelves againſt freſh Troops that pour'd in upon 'em, and the Viſir not being able to come to a general Deciſion, among the Mountains where his Enemies lay entrenched, the <hi>Seraskier</hi> was routed, his Infantry broken, almoſt all the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> ſlain, not one being able to get into the place.</p>
            <p>The Viſir enrag'd at this Repulſe, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to put all to the venture in order to force the Enemies lines, call'd a Council of War; where <hi>Siaous,</hi> who cunningly carry'd on his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treague, feign'd at firſt to applaud the Viſir's Reſolution, and threw upon the <hi>Seraskier</hi> all
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:95750:48"/>the blame of the ſucceſs; but then his own Creatures which he had ready prepar'd ſtarting contrary Sentiments, ſupported by reaſons that appear'd extreamly plauſible, he turn'd o' their ſide, and drew the reſt of the Officers after him. Nevertheleſs, in deſpite of their Advice, the Viſir would follow his own judgment, and got every thing in a readineſs to fall upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my next Morning. But then <hi>Siaous</hi> rais'd a kind of Sedition among the <hi>Spahi</hi>'s, ſo that the Viſir fearing to be ſet upon himſelf in the heat of the Tumult, pull'd down his Tents and remov'd three Leagues farther.</p>
            <p>He thought by this means to have calm'd their Fury, and propoſing the ſame thing a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, he ſaw 'twas impoſſible to overcome the reſiſtance of the <hi>Baſha</hi>'s. So that all he could do, in the height of his Vexation was, to pull thirty Thouſand Ducats out of a little Cheſt, and tell 'em to two Thouſand <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> who for the ſake of that ſumm, primis'd to loſe their lives every man, or to get into the Town.</p>
            <p>They march'd in the Night time, ſeconded by a part of the Army, and fell upon the Quarter of the <hi>Brandenburghs</hi> and <hi>Croates</hi> with ſo much fury, that they made all give ground be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'em, and had not the vigilance of Prince <hi>Charles</hi> put a ſtop to it, the Succour had infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly cut their way through; but he having drawn up his whole Army in Battalia, after a bloody ſlaughter, the <hi>Turks</hi> were repuls'd, by reaſon that eight thouſand <hi>Spahi</hi>'s refus'd to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:95750:49"/>obey the Viſir's Orders; ſo that of two Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand there were not above four Hundred <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> that could force their way over the bodies of the ſlain into the Town, the reſt being all devour'd by the Sword.</p>
            <p>But this Diſobedience of the <hi>Spahi</hi>'s remain'd not unpuniſh'd; for the Viſir having caus'd ſome of the moſt Mutinous to be empla'd, he call'd another Council, and told 'em, that he did not call 'em to deliberate, but to ſhew 'em the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's Order, which was, rather to venture all then loſe <hi>Buda;</hi> and that a <hi>Moor</hi> having ſwam the River had brought him Letters from <hi>Abdi</hi> to let him know that he could hold out but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few days longer.</p>
            <p>Having diſmiſs'd this Council, he caus'd his Army to march, and reapproach'd the Lines, and having drawn up his Army in Battallia, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall on, he detach'd a thouſand <hi>Spahi's,</hi> two thouſand <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> and two thouſand <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> to begin a falſe attaque on the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> ſide, while he fell upon the <hi>Bavarians</hi> Quarter with the body of the Army.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> being well inform'd of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir's deſign, diſplay'd his Courage, his Wiſdom and Experience to a Miracle. The falſe attack was ſo violent, and the medley ſo hot, that the Prince had his Camp Adjutant ſlain cloſe by him; the beſieged alſo made a vigorous Sally. But Prince <hi>Charles</hi> had order'd every thing with ſo much prudence and fore-ſight, that the <hi>Turks</hi> were repuls'd with great loſs, at the ſame time
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:95750:49"/>that they who began the falſe attack were beaten and diſperſs'd. So that the Viſir, who at that very moment was about to have fallen upon the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> found ſuch a Pannick fear among his men, becauſe they ſaw the Count of <hi>Schaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>femberg</hi>'s Volant Camp paſs the <hi>Danaw</hi> Bridge, that 'was impoſſible for him to command the Obedience of the Soldiers; inſomuch that he was conſtrain'd to retire without making any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther attempt.</p>
            <p>This laſt Blow put him into a Fury, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſcovering that the two <hi>Baſhas</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the falſe attack, had not done their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he commanded their Heads to be ſtruck off, and to repair his loſſes, he ſent to an <hi>Aga,</hi> who commanded ſix thouſand <hi>Janiſaries</hi> at <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> to joyn him with all ſpeed; and to other <hi>Baſha</hi>'s he ſent Orders to ſpare him what men they could.</p>
            <p>But while he was preparing for new Efforts, Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> perceiving the Breaches open and level enough for a general Aſſault, he ſtorm'd the Town in three ſeveral places; the Renegat <hi>Abdi</hi> was kill'd upon the Breach, and the place carry'd, and nothing eſcap'd the Sword of the victorious Soldiers, but what the generoſity of the Princes could ſave from their Fury.</p>
            <p>The Viſir, at his Wits end for the loſs of ſo important a place, retir'd under the Guns of <hi>Eſſeek,</hi> and there without paſſing the <hi>Drave,</hi> entrench'd himſelf. Prince <hi>Charles</hi> follow'd him, but could not force him to a Battel, which
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:95750:50"/>would have been a vain thing againſt a victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Army. Therefore he kept himſelf cloſe in his Entrenchments, where he had the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to receive the News of the loſs of <hi>Segeden,</hi> and ſome other places of leſs conſequence; but at length repaſſing the <hi>Drave</hi> in his Return to <hi>Belgrade,</hi> the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> burnt the Bridge of <hi>Eſleck,</hi> and ſo ended the moſt glorious of all Prince <hi>Charles</hi>'s Campaigns.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the ſad tidings of the loſs of <hi>Buda,</hi> and other places, were carry'd to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople;</hi> which wrought upon the People the full effect that Prince <hi>Soliman, Siaous</hi> and <hi>Cuproli</hi> deſir'd. But the Viſir was too well fix'd in the Sultan's favour, not to find him graciouſly inclin'd to hear his juſtifications; which was the only Conſolation left him in the heap of his Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for that while he lay at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by Letters from the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> that the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan had ſeen <hi>Abra,</hi> and that he was deſperately in love with her; nevertheleſs, that the fair <hi>Muſcovite</hi> was reſolv'd to be conſtant to him, though <hi>Mahomet</hi> had order'd her to be remov'd into the <hi>Serraglio</hi> of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> call'd the <hi>Serraglio</hi> of Looking Glaſſes; however in regard the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan did not proſecute his Amours like a <hi>Turk,</hi> but as a courtly and generous Prince, he did not believe that <hi>Mahomet</hi> would ſeek to enjoy her againſt her will, but that he would make uſe of his Courtſhip to win her Affection.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore leave the Viſir a while at <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade,</hi> ſettling Affairs in the beſt method he could,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:95750:50"/>and making all the haſt his buſineſs would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to return and give the Sultan an Account of a Campaign, the ill ſucceſs of which he was ſure could not be imputed to his ill Conduct; and let us ſee how things were carry'd at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> between <hi>Abra, Mahomet</hi> and <hi>Soliman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sultan, who before he had ſeen the young <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> but barely upon the relation of the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtangi Bachi,</hi> had plac'd her by an augmentation of her Penſion in the Rank of his Favourites, preſs'd the Kiſler to ſatisfy his amorous Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; ſo that the Eunuch after long delays, which tended only to give motion to the Jealouſy of the Sultaneſs <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> could no longer defer fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Duty of his Employment; and therefore he told the Sultan that <hi>Abra</hi> being in perfect health was now in a Condition to appear, and that the next morning ſhe would be walking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sultaneſſes Terraſs.</p>
            <p>The Eunuch however was ſo crafty, that he would not permit any more then eight or ten to walk along with her, who being every one of 'em exquiſite Beauties, he was in hopes that ſuch a dazle might puzle the Sultan's heart, and cauſe an amorous diverſion. He alſo oblig'd 'em to add to their natural Charms whatever Artifice could procure, while <hi>Abra,</hi> who had no deſigns of conqueſt, appear'd with all the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſneſs that modeſty and decency would permit her.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:95750:51"/>
            <p>However he could not ſo order it, but that the Sultan found her much more aſſable then all the reſt, who would have been much more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to have anſwer'd his deſires. After a turn upon the Terraſs, which was only ſpent in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral converſe, and in expreſſing his ſurprize at the ſight of ſo much Beauty, and his Aſtoniſhment that he had not ſeen nor taken notice of her at her firſt Entrance into the Serraglio; they walk'd down into the Garden of Fountains, where a noble Collation was prepar'd in a <hi>Grotto,</hi> adorn'd with Coral and Mother of Pearl, and wherein the Water ſported after a thouſand delightful manners. After this Entertainment, <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who had not till then apply'd himſelf particularly to the <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> took her from the reſt of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who retyr'd, and leading her into a green Arbour, he declar'd to her thoſe Motions, to which he imagin'd ſhe would not have teſtify'd the leaſt coyneſs.</p>
            <p>But he was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd to find in her that coldneſs and indifferency, which he leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; however he imputed it to that awe which the Majeſty of a Sultan might imprint in her up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt ſight; and therefore being endu'd with a Noble and Courtly mind, he forbore to preſs her, in hopes that the pleaſures he ſhould receive from the hands of Love, would be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more ſweet then thoſe for which he was beholding to his Power and Authority.</p>
            <p>The next morning at the time that <hi>Abra</hi> roſe, the Kiſler attended by ſix Eunuchs enter'd her
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:95750:51"/>Chamber, and kneeling with one knee kiſs'd a gold Box enrich'd with Diamonds, which he held between both his hands, and without ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Word ſet it upon her Toylet, and at the ſame time the ſix Eunuchs, who had every one a Basket of Gold Filagreene, with a Preſent in each, ſet down the ſix Baskets by <hi>Abra,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a profound Bow retyr'd, leaving the Kiſler alone with her. <hi>Abra,</hi> who underſtood well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough the meaning of all this Serraglio-Mumme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, could not forbear weeping, and caſting a ſorrowful Eye uyon the Kiſler: Muſt it then be, dear <hi>Agaſi,</hi> ſaid ſhe, muſt it then be, that this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening my heart and the Viſir's muſt receive their deaths wound from your hand.</p>
            <p>I betray not, ſaid the Kiſler, neither your Love, nor the ſincere friendſhip I have for the Vizir, I only diſcharge the indiſpenſable Duty of my Employment, wherein if I ſhould fail, I ſhould diſable my ſelf from ſerving yee.</p>
            <p>Ah, what ſervice can you do me, cruel <hi>Agaſi,</hi> reply'd <hi>Abra,</hi> when you have once deliver'd me over to the Sultan. As a ſlave, reply'd the <hi>Kisler,</hi> I owe my Obedience to the Sultan, and as a Friend my Service to the Viſir, and I fullfil both theſe Duties, by telling you in favour of his Highneſs, that if Ambition could tempt yee, and that you could but conform to the Sultan's Love, there would be nothing wanting to the Grandeurs which he has deſign'd you. But if your Love be ſtill more prevalent on your heart then theſe ambitious Proſpects, I muſt tell you
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:95750:52"/>alſo in his behalf, that you have no more to do but to perſiſt in your Coldneſs for <hi>Mahomet:</hi> I know him: he loves to be beholding to his Merit and his Paſſion, and not to his Power, nor does his Preſumption ever call violence to the ſuccour of his luſt, he will trye allways of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion to gain your affection, but he will never proceed to conſtraint; act according to theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, and truſt the beſt Friend the Viſir has.</p>
            <p>Ah, dear <hi>Agaſi,</hi> reply'd <hi>Abra,</hi> you reſtore me to Life, and never doubt but I will rather loſe it a Thouſand times then prove unfaithful to your Friend. I muſt alſo acknowledge to you, that ſince I have heard what you have ſaid to me, 'tis ſomething of a Pleaſure to me to ſee my ſelf belov'd by the Sultan, becauſe it afford's me a pleaſing Opportunity to ſacrifice to the Viſir all <hi>Mahomet's</hi> Grandeur. May nothing Extinguiſh ſo noble a flame, reply'd the Kiſler; but it will be neceſſary, Madam, added he, that you read the Sultan's Letter, and that I carry him your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. 'Tis in that Box. <hi>Abra</hi> open'd the Box; and found a Letter Written in Purple Characters upon White Taffata, Embroider'd with Gold, and folded up in a Handkercher of moſt Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Workmanſhip, where after ſhe had open'd it, ſhe read the following Expreſſions.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:95750:52"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Sultan <hi>Mahomet</hi> To the Sultaneſs <hi>Abra Mulè.</hi> May the Prophet cover yee with all manner of Proſperities.</head>
                  <p>MY Pen gives you this Auguſt Title, before I have obtain'd that you ſhould receive it from the Hands of Love. That Love which I have conceiv'd for you is equal to your Beauty, and it is ſufficient to tell yee, that ſince there never was a Beauty ty ſo accompliſh'd, my Love ſhall ſolely act to merit yours; your Coldneſs tells me that you know the Extent of your Charms, and that they are of a high Value, when they make a Sultan ſigh; but my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment ſhall no leſs Eſteem the Sight which you ſhall ſpare to</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Mahomet</hi> Sultan.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Would to Heaven, ſaid <hi>Abra,</hi> that <hi>Mahomet</hi> would be as good as his word, and that he would keep within the Bounds which he preſcribes himſelf. But, added ſhe, caſting a wiſhful look upon the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> is there no way to be diſpenc'd with from writting to him? That would be the way, reply'd the <hi>Kiſler</hi> to ruin all: Nor dare I look the Sultan in the Face unleſs I carry him your Anſwer. Thereupon <hi>Abra</hi> ſet Pen to Paper and wrote the following Billet to <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:95750:53"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Abra Mulè <hi>to Sultan</hi> Mahomet.</head>
                  <p>AMong ſo many Slaves who aſpire to nothing more then the favours which your Highneſs is pleas'd profuſely to beſtow upon me, why Sir, do you deſign. 'em for a Heart that is not capable to make a ſuitable Return? I ſee the Character of a Vertue ſo magnanimous dazlingly ſhinning in the Letter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you have honour'd me, that I pitty your Love for the Unfortunate Choice it has made. Spare me Sir, the ſorrow for being ungrateful, and be contented with the moſt profound Eſteem that Womankind can have for a moſt Generous <hi>Monarch,</hi> and ſuffer to be at quiet the Heart of the Inſenſible</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Abra Mulè.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Sultan, who valu'd himſelf for being an Artiſt in the Curioſities of Courtſhip, found ſomething in this Billet wherewith to flatter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that this ſame firſt Reluctancy was onely an artificial Slight to enflame his Paſſion ſo much the more. And therefore he undertook to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh it by regular Attacks; and his firſt care was to conceal from the Sultaneſs, the Methods which his Love ſhould oblige him to take.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd no anſwer to his Billet, ſought all the ways imaginable to ſee <hi>Abra.</hi> She was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom'd to walk in a private Garden, which conſiſted onely of a Bowling green, and a Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:95750:53"/>of Paliſado's. <hi>Soliman</hi> therefore had ſcrew'd himſelf into the Friendſhip of one of the <hi>Boſtangi</hi>'s that were wont to work there; and by him it was, that he was inform'd of her frequent walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there.</p>
            <p>The Prince under pretence of a bare Curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, made ſo many Preſents and Promiſes to this old <hi>Boſtangi,</hi> that he conſented to furniſh him with a Habit of his Companions, and to let him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Garden after the Hour of third Prayers, provided he hid himſelf in a nick or hollow Seat which he fitted for him, in the body of one of the Paliſado's of the Labyrinth; aſſuring him that that was the part of the Garden which <hi>Abra</hi> moſt uſually frequented.</p>
            <p>This contrivance was put in execution to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liman</hi>'s wiſh: <hi>Abra</hi> fail'd not to come, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe had taken a Turn in the Bowling-Green, ſhe enter'd into the center of the Ladyrinth, where ſhe ſate down, together with her Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, upon a Bank of Turf, which adjoyn'd to the Receptacle of the Fountain.</p>
            <p>She had receiv'd the Evening before a very tender Letter from the Sultan, and fearing leaſt at length he ſhould come to exert his Love like a Tyrant, ſhe choſe this time to condole her Misfortunes in <hi>Sarai</hi>'s Company, and to impart her Sorrows to her for the ill ſucceſs of the Viſir.</p>
            <p>No ſooner were they ſate down, but <hi>Abra,</hi> continuing the Diſcourſe which they had had before, Be you judge, dear <hi>Sarai,</hi> ſaid ſhe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be poſſible for a Woman to be expos'd
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:95750:54"/>to greater Misfortunes. 'Tis not anough that Heaven has deſtm'd me to Love the Viſir to that degree that nothing can be more belov'd; that this Love was not inſpir'd into me till I was ſacrific'd to diſmal Slavery; that the Viſir, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his Valour and Conduct has miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry'd in all his Enterprizes; that his Misfortunes expoſe him to the Murmurs of the People, and perhaps to the Sultan's frowns; but that ſtill to the heap of my Misfortunes and my Sorrows for his ill ſucceſs, I muſt be yet more afflicted with the troubleſome Paſſion of Prince <hi>Soliman;</hi> and then to the accompliſhment of my Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Sultan has ſeen me, and is in Love with me.</p>
            <p>What was then Prince <hi>Soliman</hi>'s aſtoniſhment and grief may readily be conjectur'd. He found his Love diſarm'd, the Viſir belov'd, and as a ſurpluſage of Afflictions he perceiv'd he had a new and more dangerous Rival, the Sultan him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. While his heart lay drown'd in theſe deep inundations of Diſpair and Grief, <hi>Sarai</hi> purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Diſcourſe, Heaven uſually reſerves, ſaid ſhe, her greateſt-Misfortunes for the greateſt Souls. But what reaſon have you to make ſuch loud Complaints? You love, and are belov'd; may not the Viſir's Courage recover his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; the Sultan loves him, and excuſes him already: And what need Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> diſturb yee, conſidering how little you eſteem his love, and his want of power to moleſt yee: As for the Sultan, you know he ſcorns to make any
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:95750:54"/>Attempts upon your heart, but by ways of Love. And therefore never abandon your ſelf to the agitations of a Deſpair, that proceeds rather from Imagination then any real Grounds.</p>
            <p>Ah! dear <hi>Sarai,</hi> my Paſſion is mounted to that degree, that if the Viſir cannot find a means to releaſe me from this ſlavery, or that the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's Luſt tranſports him to the leaſt violence, a Dagger ſhall puniſh my heart for all the Vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations it has put me to. Alaſs! Into what ſeas of Grief will it not plunge the Viſir? What Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies and Fears will overwhelm him, when he underſtands that <hi>Mahomet</hi> is his Rival, he that was ſo vehemently jealous of Prince <hi>Soliman?</hi> Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ſaid <hi>Sarai,</hi> I never perceiv'd that you had the leaſt ſpark of love for that Prince. Who I, reply'd <hi>Abra,</hi> I knew the worth of Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> I could not blame his Paſſion for me; I admir'd the exceſs of it, that caus'd him to expoſe his head, that he might diſcover it to me; beſides that I am ſo unfortunate to owe my Life to his preſervation; all this might prevail ſomething o're a heart that was not prepoſſeſs'd. But mine is not my own, nothing can deprive his Rival of it; and ſeeing then they muſt hate each other, ſeeing they know themſelves to be Rivals judge thou how hateful that Prince muſt be to me, and how careful I ought to be to avoid his company.</p>
            <p>How extraordinary ſoever <hi>Soliman</hi>'s trouble might be, this Confeſſion however left him ſome room to flatter his hopes, and imagining that the Opportunity might be favourable to ſome new
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:95750:55"/>Effort, he was about to ſhew himſelf from the Paliſado, when a great noiſe gave him to underſtand that the Sultan was approaching. The Sultan took a turn or two, and being inform'd that <hi>Abra</hi> was in the Labyrinth, thither he went: She roſe up, but <hi>Mahomet</hi> engag'd her to reſeat herſelf upon a Bank of Turfs, ſo near to <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> that he might be almoſt heard to breath. <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſate down by her, and they had a long and courtly Conference together, which termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated on the Sultan's part only in amorous Importunities, and in reſpectful and modeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials on <hi>Abra</hi>'s ſide. At length the Sultan roſe up, gave his hand to the fair <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> and having led her to the Garden door, he went off through another with the <hi>Boſtangi Baſha,</hi> to communicate ſome Intelligence to him which he had receiv'd.</p>
            <p>It may be eaſily imagin'd in what condition Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> was, and what various Agitations turmoyl'd his heart. How! ſaid he, have I two Rivals at one time? One of which is belov'd, and the other has all the freedom imaginable to declare his Paſſion, and is able to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf happy when ever he pleaſes to make uſe of his Power, while ſhe is inſenſible of my flames, and it is my Misfortune that I cannot meet with an Opportunity to make known my noble fires. No—'tis impoſſible for me to continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a ſultry Violence, nor to ſuffer the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of two Rivals both at one time.</p>
            <p>He was then labouring under the Tumults of his thoughts, and left his ſtation poſſeſs'd with
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:95750:55"/>as much fury as Love: but in regard the <hi>Boſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi,</hi> who had plac'd him in his convenience was without, he was oblig'd to ſtay till the dusk of the Evening began to confound the ſight, and render the Objects of it leſs diſcernable, and then he made a ſhift to eſeape; but he could not do it ſo dextrouſly, but one of the <hi>Boſtangi Baſha</hi>'s Eunuchs perceiv'd that a Man had hid himſelf in the Lybyrinth while the Sultan was there, of which the Sultan was inform'd; and though it could not be diſcover'd who the Perſon was who had ventur'd to that degree, yet in regard that Love is always ingenious to afflict it ſelf, it ſoon came into <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s head, that <hi>Abra</hi>'s cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him muſt needs be the effect of ſome my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Love; that his aſſiduity to get into the Labyrinth was the Effect of that Love, that it muſt be ſome unknown Lover that had been ſo daring, and never ſuſpecting the Prince his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he reſolv'd to prevent the Conſequences of ſuch an Intreague, and to that purpoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the Kiſler the ſame day to carry <hi>Abra</hi> over the ſtreight of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> and ſhut her up in the Serraglio of Looking-glaſſes.</p>
            <p>The Eunuch could not avoy'd the putting this Order in Execution, tho' it griev'd him to the Soul, and broke all the meaſures he had taken to ſerve the Viſir: for that being oblig'd to remain in the Grand Serraglio near <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Perſon, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio of Looking-Glaſſes was govern'd by the <hi>Kiſler Kiaſi,</hi> who is a kind of Deputy to the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi;</hi> and becauſe not being able to go
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:95750:56"/>thither, but when he was order'd by the Sultan to attend him, <hi>Abra</hi> was now deſtitute of the Conſolation and Advice which he was wont to give her. So that all the good he could do her was only to place ſuch Slaves about her as ſhe deſir'd, and Eunuchs for whoſe fidelity he could be anſwerable.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was all in an Uproar, by reaſon of the continual bad Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings that follow'd one another of the Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes of the Campaign; and <hi>Siaous</hi>'s and <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proli</hi>'s Friends ſpread abroad Reports ſo diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to the Viſir's Conduct, that he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Object of the Peoples Averſion and Scorn.</p>
            <p>But when the Prince underſtood by <hi>Marama,</hi> that the Sultan had remov'd <hi>Abra,</hi> and put her into the Serraglio of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> and had caus'd her to take upon her the name of Sultaneſs, his jealouſy made him believe that ſhe had Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render'd to the Love of this new Rival, and his deſpair not being able to imagin any other way to enjoy her, but by making himſelf Maſter of his Brother's Throne, from that very Moment he took a Reſolution to pull down his Brother, and to take the Advantage of the Conjuncture to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the exaſperated minds of the People to Revolt.</p>
            <p>His Myſterious applying himſelf to the ſtudy of the Alcoran, had made him take particular care always to inſinuate himſelf into the Friendſhip of the <hi>Mufti</hi>'s, who are the Soveraign <hi>Pontiffs</hi> of the Law, and to be in a Continual familiarity with the <hi>Imans,</hi> who are the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:95750:56"/>that hold forth in the <hi>Moſquees,</hi> and with all the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Clergy; by which means he had gain'd their Hearts by the affected ſhews of a ſuperſtitious Devotion, and by the Liberality of his Alms of which he made them the Truſtees; ſo that 'twas no hard thing for him to incenſe thoſe ſenſeleſs Eccleſiaſtics, and put 'em upon rayling publickly againſt the Authors of all the Diſorders in the Empire, under pretence of Preaching Repentance to the People.</p>
            <p>From the Abuſe of this falſe Zeal, it was that the firſt Inclinations to Revolt, ſlidd themſelves into Male-contented Breaſts. But Miſchief was yet a great way off, and therefore before they could fall upon the Perſon of the Sultan, there was a neceſſity of ruining the Viſir, who was his Zealous Favourite, and who poſſeſs'd the hearts of the Principal Officers of the Empire.</p>
            <p>The Prince was therefore perſwaded that the loſs of <hi>Buda,</hi> that the victorious Progreſſes of the Chriſtians, ev'n to the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> and that the Murmurs of the People againſt his Chief Miniſter, would wean the Sultan's Affection from him. But he was ſurpriz'd when he ſaw the Viſir arriv'd at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> with a Writting ſign'd by all the Principal Officers of the Army, and <hi>Siaous</hi> himſelf, who was forc'd to ſwim with the ſtream, for fear of Diſcovering his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and that this Writing was an <hi>Encomium</hi> of the Viſir's Conduct, prudence and Courage, and which juſtify'd him in every particular that could be Objected againſt him.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:95750:57"/>
            <p>The Sultan, who had always had a kindneſs for him, was overjoy'd that his Souldiers gave his Favourite ſo advantageous a Teſtimony: He receiv'd him with open Armes; and order'd him to haſten more powerful Preparations, that he might the next Campaign repair the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes which were not to be imputed to any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in Him.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> who began to buckle the Spurrs of his Ambition with the Impetuous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of his Love, and who by the loſs of one of his Rivals, was deſirous to haſten the downfall of the other, finding that whatever <hi>Siaous</hi> and <hi>Cuproli</hi> had done during the Campaign prov'd fruitleſs, labour'd under unimaginable Vexations. <hi>Siaous</hi> and <hi>Cuproli</hi> were arriv'd at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> ſo order'd it, as to meet 'em both in a place, wither he came to 'em in diſguize.</p>
            <p>Preſently the Prince told 'em, that after what they had done the laſt Campaign, things were reduc'd to that Extremity, that either they muſt ruin the Vizir, or expect all three to periſh by the Bow-ſtring; that there was no time to be loſt; that ſince the Loſs of <hi>Buda,</hi> of ſuch Importance to the Empire, wrought no effect upon the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, but that his Minion was ſtill as much in favour as ever, there was but one way to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, which was to make themſelves abſolute Maſters of the Army; that they ſhould cauſe 'em to revolt in the midſt of the Campaign, and oblige 'em to demand the Head of the Grand Viſir, and of all his principle Friends; Seeing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:95750:57"/>then, that the Sultan affraid of himſelf, would be forc'd to ſacrifice him to his own Security; and that then the Seal of the Empire could fall into no other hands, but either <hi>Siaous</hi>'s or <hi>Cuproli</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>The two Baſha's acknowledg'd that the Prince ſpoke nothing but what was reaſon, however they did not yet penetrate into all his Deſigns; and <hi>Soliman,</hi> like a crafty Politician, was deſirous to render 'em ſtill more Guilty before he impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to 'em the laſt Crime they were to commit. All this while they follow'd the Intereſts of their own Ambition, and as the firſt ſteps they had made engag'd them to puſh forward the ruin of the Viſir, or elſe patiently to ſubmit to their own deſtruction, they promis'd <hi>Soliman</hi> to go on with the project, of which he had given the draught.</p>
            <p>The favourable reception which the Sultan gave the Viſir, and the augmentation of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and his Credit did not abate his deadly Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to find that his Maſter was his formidable Rival, in whoſe power it was to make him hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. Nor was the Kiſler any longer able to give him the Opportunities of ſeeing his beloved Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs. All that he could do, was cunningly to conveigh his Billets to her by <hi>Saria</hi>'s means, and the fidelity of the Eunuchs which he had plac'd about her. So that the Viſir having no other conſolation left, deſir'd his friend to get the following Letter deliver'd to her.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:95750:58"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The</hi> Unfortunate <hi>to his dear</hi> Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nate.</head>
                  <p>BY what Cruelty of Fate, my Dear <hi>Abra,</hi> muſt I be the moſt unhappy of your Lovers, when I am the moſt be lov'd! You refuſe the <hi>Sultan's</hi> Vows, but he has the pleaſure of ſeeing you when he pleaſes; and if he be not the moſt happy, yet he may be ſo when ever he has a mind to it. Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> may comfort himſelf for your indifferency, with the pleaſure that he had to ſave your life; only the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Viſir, as much belov'd as he is, can neither ſee you, nor pay you any ſervice. The <hi>Sultan</hi> continues his favours to me. Alas! Let him take 'em from me, and reſtore me the Bleſſing of which he has depriv'd me; all his Empire is not worth a ſigh from your Lips. If you love me ſtill, you will judge of my Sorrows by your own Grief; they are deadly, if Heaven does not furniſh me with ſome Expedient to break your Chains.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The <hi>Kiſler</hi> caus'd this Letter to be faithfully deliver'd: In the mean time the <hi>Sultan,</hi> maugre all the Vigilancy of the jealous Sultaneſs, found out pretences to go to <hi>Calcedon.</hi> For the murmurs of the People, and the inſolent Harangues of the <hi>Imans,</hi> afforded him anow; and therefore faign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not to be ſafe in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> he frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly croſt the Streight, and to give the more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to his Pretences, he many time held the <hi>Divan</hi> in the <hi>Serraglio</hi> of Looking-Glaſſes, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:95750:58"/>then he order'd the Viſir to attend him.</p>
            <p>One Evening that he went thither with his chief Miniſters, and that they two were juſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into his Cabinet to prepare what was fit to be propounded the next day to the <hi>Divan,</hi> they were amaz'd to hear the loud Cries and Skreekes of Women quite through the Galleries, at what time they were inform'd that a ſuddain Fire was broken forth in the Body of the Building, and that the Flames beſieg'd the principal apparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on every ſide, which was the appartiment where the Sultan had plac'd his fair <hi>Muſcovite;</hi> ſo that haſtning thither, together with the Viſir and their Train, they found the Conflagration ſo violent, that neither Slaves nor Eunuchs durſt venture thorough to ſuccour the Women who were in extream Danger.</p>
            <p>The Sultan's Voice and his Orders encourag'd 'em, but the Viſir underſtanding which was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra</hi>'s Appartiment, was the firſt that flew to her Aid; and having ſought and found her alone in a Swoon in her Chamber, he took her in his Arms, and ſeeing that the violence of the Flames had ſeiz'd that part at which he enter'd, he made his may through Clouds of Smoak, and through another Gallery which led to an Apparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a good way from the Fire.</p>
            <p>The Sultan, who neither ſaw the Viſir return, nor knew what was become of <hi>Abra,</hi> thought her loſt, and diſplay'd his Sorrow at a more then uſual Rate; ſome Women that were ſav'd could tell no tydings of her; neither could <hi>Sarai</hi> her
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:95750:59"/>ſelf make any Diſcovery, who was not with her Miſtreſs when the Fire broke out.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Abra</hi> being carry'd to the furtheſt end of that Appartiment, which the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult had quite Empty'd, recover'd her Spirits, and found her ſelf in the Viſir's Arms. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe was ſtill in an Amazement, nor could ſhe apprehend the meaning of ſuch a ſurprizing Adventure. But the Viſir, who was not willing to loſe ſo precious an Opportunity, threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at her Feet, and Embracing her with no leſs Ardour then Reſpect; Ah, Madam, ſaid he, you behold once more your Unfortunate Lover; Heaven could not remove the Obſtacles that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd you inviſible, but by expoſing your life to the moſt dreadful of all Dangers; nothing but a miraculous accident could afford me this oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſeeing you. Lucky Danger! Favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Meeting! But may I know, Madam, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your heart be as conſtant as mine: I was affraid of a Rival who had no power; but Fate has found me out another who can do whatever he pleaſes; have I no cauſe to fear neither his Love, nor his Power?</p>
            <p>His Empire, anſwer'd <hi>Abra,</hi> may be abſolute over every thing elſe, but o're my heart. But as for my heart, I preſerve it for your ſelf till Death, and I will loſe a thouſand Lives, before I prove unfaithful to you. But, Sir, will you ſuffer me to periſh in his Fetters, are they ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible that you cannot releaſe me?</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:95750:59"/>
            <p>Ah, Madam, reply'd the Viſir, there is not any Reaſon, or danger that can hinder me from doing it, if it be your deſire, and this is the moſt favourable opportunity in the world if you can reſolve to make uſe of it. The whole <hi>Serraglio</hi> is in an upproar, the Sultan will believe yee loſt in the Flames, ſtay but a minute here, and Ile go fetch one of my white Eunuch's Habits, and ſet yee out of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> through the door of one of the Gardens, of which I have the Key; for the reſt never trouble your ſelf, Love, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Opportunities will direct us.</p>
            <p>How odd and dangerous ſoever this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal appear'd, ſuch was the cruel Condition that <hi>Abra</hi> was in, that without any more ado ſhe accepted the offer. The Viſir was ſoon furniſh'd with the Habit he deſir'd, and having diſguiz'd her, he let her out at the Garden Door, and deliver'd her into the charge of one of his moſt faithful Eunuchs, who not knowing who ſhe was, but taking her for ſome new Eunuch that had been preſented to his Maſter, put her into a little Fiſher Boat with a diſign to land her in <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Viſir, having thus entruſted his Treaſure to the Fidelity of that Slave, went to attend the Sultan, a thouſand accidents preſenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for pretences to excuſe his Abſence. <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> was at his wits end; though the Fire was quite Extinguiſh'd, by leaving the Flames to feed upon the grand Appartiment, while they ſtopt it from going any farther, by pulling down ſome
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:95750:60"/>building between that and the reſt of the <hi>Serra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio;</hi> but ſearch was made for the <hi>Muſcovite</hi> in every corner, ſo that at length the Sultan gave her over for loſt; and that which confirm'd him the more in that Opinion was, that after the Fire was put out, they found the remainders of five or ſix Bodies.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Abra</hi>'s Veſſel row'd directly to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> by the bright Rays of the Moon, and ſhe flatter'd her ſelf that ſhe ſhould now ſoon enjoy the only Perſon whom ſhe Lov'd above all the World; but there is nothing more to be wonder'd at then the Fantaſtick changes of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
            <p>The News of the Fire in the <hi>Serraglio</hi> of Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſſes was brought to the chief Sultaneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Midnight; therefore becauſe ſhe kept the chiefeſt part of her Treaſure there, and for that ſhe knew beſides that the Sultan was gone thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, theſe two diſturbing reaſons oblidg'd her to ſend for the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> and take her <hi>Saick</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, with orders to croſs the Water to <hi>Calce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> But no ſooner had ſhe put to Sea, but by the dawning light of day, they diſcover'd a little Fiſher Boat making for the <hi>Europaean</hi> ſhore; upon which the Sultaneſs who was willing to hear News, conſtrain'd the Viſir's ſlave to come aboard her Veſſel. Preſently ſhe ask'd him ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Queſtions, and finding him tripping in his Anſwers, ſhe ſent for the White Eunuch, with whom he ſaid he was entruſted.</p>
            <p>No ſooner was he come into the Cabin in
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:95750:60"/>Diſguiſe, but the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> who accompany'd the Sultaneſs knew <hi>Abra</hi> notwithſtanding her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe; and the <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> charm'd with the Beauty of the Eunuch, declar'd that ſhe would keep him to attend upon her. But the <hi>Kiſler</hi> being a man of a cunning, ſharp and preſent Wit, and quickly conceiving that <hi>Abra</hi> had made her eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape by ſome contrivance of the <hi>Viſirs,</hi> he knew that if the Sultaneſs ſhould carry her back to <hi>Calcedon,</hi> 'twould be the ruin of both the two Lovers, and therefore never heſitating what courſe to take, he put all the People out of the Cabin, excepting the White Eunuch, and that done, the <hi>Keſler</hi> taking <hi>Abra</hi> by the hand, and ſquee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing it in his own to prevent ſurprize, he look'd upon the Sultaneſs, and putting the Queſtion to her as it were in jeſt, may a man rely upon yee, Madam, ſhould he truſt ye with a ſecret which you would be glad to know? I had thought, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Sultaneſs you had known me better then to doubt it. Upon your word then, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, I muſt put ſo much confidence in you, as to let you underſtand that this fair Eunuch is the lovely <hi>Muſcovite</hi> with whom the Sultan is ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately in love, but who no leſs obſtinately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes to correſpond with his Amour. I find ſhe has taken her opportunity in the confuſion caus'd by the Fire to get away. Would you, Madam, carry her back to <hi>Mahomet</hi> whom ſhe avoids, and who without queſtion hunts after her in a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand diſquiets of mind? My duty indeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that I ſhould ſeize her, and deliver her
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:95750:61"/>back into his hands; but I am too much your friend to take that courſe. 'Tis for you, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, to do as you think ſitting; and if you will take the Advice of a Slave, that is ſolely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to your intereſts, I would not have yee let go this happy opportunity that Heaven has put into your hands; you may at once deliver your ſelf from the fears of ſo amiable a Rivaleſs, and at the ſame time releaſe her from all her Pains. Bury this important ſecret in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found ſilence, and content your ſelf with allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her a ſafe ſanctuary from the Sultan's Paſſion, which at length perhaps may cool and return to its firſt object.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> confirm'd by <hi>Abra</hi>'s confeſſion, who inſtead of revealing to her the ſecret of the Viſir, gave her to underſtand, that ſhe had of her own head made her eſcape from the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, embrac'd her, and promis'd her all manner of favour and ſecurity, and by concert with the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> ſent her to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to a place where ſhe was abſolute Miſtreſs, and where ſhe kept her conceal'd under an unknown Name. However ſhe purſu'd her firſt intentions, went to <hi>Calcedon,</hi> and return'd with the Sultan, who was more perplex'd for the loſs of <hi>Abra,</hi> then for all his other misfortunes. On the other ſide, the <hi>Kiſler</hi> inform'd the Viſir of what had befallen the <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covite,</hi> which peirc'd him to the Soul, finding that he had loſt her again, tho' he thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a competent gainer in having releas'd her from ſlavery to the Sultan.</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:95750:61"/>
            <p>During theſe amorous motions, the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the Campaign were carry'd on might and main, and the Viſir left nothing omitted that lay in his Power to put himſelf into ſuch a condition that he might repair his loſſes; while <hi>Siaous</hi> and <hi>Cuproli</hi> prepar'd the minds of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers every where for mutiny, inſtilling it into their heads, neither to have any confidence in the Grand Viſir, which is the Soul of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor any eſteem for him, which preſerves reſpect.</p>
            <p>The Viſir ſtay'd but a while at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> for the Sultan oblig'd him to haſten away for <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade;</hi> and this it was that occaſion'd the report, as if he never had been there. His firſt care was to repair the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> notwithſtanding thoſe difficulties which appear'd unſurmounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and ſoon after he put himſelf at the head of his Army.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> having rendevouz'd together above Sixty Thouſand Men, advanc'd at the head of 'em, and reſolv'd to decide the Fate of the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign by a pitch'd Battle, and to that purpoſe croſs'd the <hi>Drave.</hi> But the Vizir, who had been more ſpeedy in his march then they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, came and Encamp'd with Fourſcore Thouſand men in view of the Chriſtian Army; and in regard he underſtood perfectly well how to make choice of his Ground, he had got the <hi>Drave</hi> upon the right, a Forreſt upon his left, <hi>Eſſeck</hi> in his rear, and an intrenchment in front,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:95750:62"/>fortify'd with a double Moat forty foot wide, and a double Rank of Paliſado's: So that he forc'd Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> after ſome Rude Encounters, to retreat for want of Proviſion. But he made his Retreat in ſo good Order, that he repaſs'd the <hi>Drave</hi> in view of the Enemy without the leaſt diſturbance, and Encampt within a league of <hi>Mohatz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Viſir, flatter'd with this firſt Advantage, and deſirous to make the beſt of it, paſt the <hi>Drave,</hi> and being poſted between <hi>Eſſeck</hi> and <hi>Darda,</hi> ſent out numerous detachments to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſs the Chriſtian Army. As for his own Camp, he had entrench'd it with a Paliſado'd moat which ſecur'd his Front, he had <hi>Eſſeck</hi> in his rear, from whence he was plentifully ſupply'd with Proviſions, the <hi>Danaw,</hi> and Impaſſable <hi>Moraſſes</hi> ſecur'd his Right Wing, and his Left was cover'd with a Wood, by the ſide of which lay a long Moraſs; ſo that it was a difficult thing for Prince <hi>Charles</hi> to venture the forcing his Camp without hazarding the loſs of his whole Army.</p>
            <p>Therefore he made uſe of all manner of ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems and motions, to try whether he could draw the Viſir from his Poſt, and bring him to a General Battel. But he, who found himſelf better ſupply'd with Proviſions then the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts, ſought to ruin 'em by frequent Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, and therefore keeping cloſe in his Camp, ſent out Parties continually to diſturb the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies Forragers, or to attack 'em in their Movements.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:95750:62"/>
            <p>But all this while he was ignorant of what <hi>Siaous</hi> was plotting in his Camp, in Conjunction with <hi>Baſha Yeghen,</hi> a Man Daring, of a Turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Seditious Spirit and the Viſir's particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Enemy, inſolent in his language, but Eloquent, gifted in perſuaſion, and who by his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar deportment had gain'd great Credit with the Souldiery. Their Deſign was to force the Viſir to a Battel, and ſo to order their Affairs that he might loſe it, that it might ſerve for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for the Souldiers to revolt.</p>
            <p>All things being thus concluded, upon the 12th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> faigning a Retreat paſs'd a narrow Lane full of Hedges that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd his March, and gave order's for his Army to embattel in the Plain of <hi>Siclos.</hi> The Viſir having Intelligence of this General motion of the Chriſtian Army, ſent away ſome conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Bodies to follow 'em, and fall upon their Rear commanded by the Elector of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> The <hi>Baſha</hi> of <hi>Arabia</hi> alſo was order'd with one part of the Army to ſecond the Detachments. But <hi>Siaous</hi> who judg'd the Opportunity proper for his deſign, preſently put the Souldiers into ſuch a fit of Murmuring, as if their General had depriv'd 'em of a certain Victory, that the Viſir finding that the <hi>Baſha</hi> acting beyond his Orders, march'd on with the Detachments, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to reſtrain the Heat of the Souldiers, drew his whole Army out of their Entrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and advanc'd directly toward the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ialiſts</hi> in Battel array.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:95750:63"/>
            <p>The Vanguard of the <hi>Turk's</hi> overtook the Rear of the Chriſtians, before they had paſs'd the narrow Lane; ſo that the whole ſtreſs of the firſt Charge fell upon the Elector of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> However, having gain'd the riſing Ground deſign'd him for his Poſt, in deſpite of all the Enemies Efforts, he ſtood firm, and Prince <hi>Charles</hi> reinforc'd him with the ſecond Line of the Vanguard, to prevent the Enemies Charging him either in Flank or Rear.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> charg'd him with great fury, and he withſtood 'em with no leſs prudence then undaunted Bravery, and venturing in the hotteſt of the Enemies firing, he was wounded in the left hand with a Musket Bullet.</p>
            <p>In the mean time Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> who was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd a great way farther, thought it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to draw the Enemy into the Plain, where they might have more Roome for Action, and ſuccour one another with more Freedom. This caus'd the Elector to quit his Ground, tho' Skirmiſhing all the while, ſo that his Rear-guard made the Left Wing equal with the Right, which Prince <hi>Charles</hi> Commanded.</p>
            <p>Preſently the whole Army of the <hi>Turks</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in Battell array, and the Princes who had now what they wiſh'd for charg'd 'em on all ſides: The Inſidels alſo fell on with great Fury, and at firſt had ſome conſiderable Advantage, having routed the <hi>Croates,</hi> and almoſt cut in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>Comercy</hi>'s Regiment; and the ſucceſs of the Ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ttel had been very dubious, had not the <hi>Spahi</hi>'s
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:95750:63"/>by the contrivance and treachery of <hi>Siaous, Yeghen,</hi> and the Baſha of <hi>Arabia,</hi> left the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> that fought againſt the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who taking his advantage of that diſorder, fell upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry oppoſite to him with an extraordinary fury. However, the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> inſtead of being brok'n, retir'd in good order as far as their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments, where at firſt they fell a firing at a prodigious rate, but not being ſeconded by the Horſe, they betook themſelves to flight, and this Rout of the <hi>Turks</hi> Right Wing ſtriking a Terrour into the Left, the Diſorder became Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the whole Army was denfeated, and the Camp. taken and pilladg'd; at what time the Vizir retreating of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> and having rally'd his ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd Troops, found he had loſt above Twenty thouſand Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Siaous</hi> would not let this Opportunity ſlip, which he had taken ſo much pains to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; ſo that the Mutiny began with the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels between the <hi>Spahi</hi>'s and the <hi>Janiſaries;</hi> but they being ſoon reunited, vented all their fury in Murmurs againſt the Viſir; who not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whence the miſchief proceeded, thought to have appeas'd 'em, by diſtributing among 'em all the Money he had. But the poiſon was too well prepar'd, and had ſpread it ſelf too far; ſo that the minds of the Souldiers being more and more envenom'd, their Clamours augmented, while the <hi>Imperialists</hi> proſecuting their Victory, made themſelves Maſters of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> and the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Drave.</hi> Nor was <hi>Siaous</hi> contented with
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:95750:64"/>ſtirring up the Souldiers to murmur, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſing them to an open Revolt, put himſelf at the Head of 'em, and <hi>Yeghen</hi> had the boldneſs to enter the Viſir's Tent, and demand in the Name of the Army the Seals of the Empire, and <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Standard, declaring, they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd no longer to obey him.</p>
            <p>This Inſolence producing a great Uproar, the Viſir made his eſcape, got by water to <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and thence poſted to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to give the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan an Account of the Campaign, <hi>Siaous</hi>'s Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, and the Condition of the Army.</p>
            <p>The Viſir having thus withdrawn himſelf, <hi>Siaous</hi> became Maſter of the Army, and depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſix Officers to demand, in the Name of the Souldiers, the Heads of the Vizir, and of all his principal Friends, of which they drew up a Liſt. The Vizir being inform'd of theſe furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Proceedings, ſent the Seals of the Empire to the Grand Teffterdar, for him to deliver 'em into the Sultan's hands, and with only one ſlave ſtole privately into <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and went to the <hi>Kiamakan</hi>'s Houſe, where the Kiſler came to him, and aſſur'd him, in the Sultan's Name, that neither his Misfortunes, nor the Mutinies of the Souldiers, had ſhaken his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; that he lov'd him; that he pitty'd him, and that he was not only reſolv'd to ſee him, but to defend him againſt the fury of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volters.</p>
            <p>However, nothſtanding all the weight of theſe Misfortunes with which the Vizer ſeem'd to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:95750:64"/>be overwhelm'd, he had ſtill his thoughts fix'd upon the fair <hi>Muſcovite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We gave an Account, how ſome few days before the departurte of the Vizir for <hi>Belgrade,</hi> ſhe fell into the Hands of the Sultaneſs <hi>Aſſeki;</hi> but the Vizir was ſo far from being able to get to her in the place, where ſhe was kept con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd, and under another Name, that he could hardly procure the delivery of a Letter to her; nor had he receiv'd any from her, though the Kiſler had had credit enough to keep <hi>Sarai</hi> about her ſtill.</p>
            <p>However he underſtood by a Eunuch, that the Sultan knew very well that ſhe was not burnt in the fire, and that he had private Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence that ſhe had made her eſcape out of the Serraglio of Looking-Glaſſes; nevertheleſs that he knew not who had contributed to her eſcape, and that all the Diligence he had us'd to find out the Place of her Retirement had prov'd fruitleſs. That Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> had been better inform'd; for that <hi>Marama</hi> who held her Correſpondencies every where, had div'd into the Secret out of a Conceit ſhe had that her eſcape was a ſtroke of the Sultaneſs's jealouſy, and that upon that diſcovery ſhe was negotiatiog with the Sultaneſs <hi>Aſſeki;</hi> with whom ſhe had intruſted the ſecret of Prince <hi>Soliman's</hi> Love, and had put it into her head that the only way to deprive <hi>Mahomet</hi> of her was to deliver her up to his Brother.</p>
            <p>This drove the Viſir to his Wits end, to ſee the utter Ruin of his Fortune and his Love both
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:95750:65"/>at one time: However the <hi>Kiſler</hi> carry'd him privately to the Sultan, who receiv'd him ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, and aſſur'd him not only of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his favour, but of his Protection againſt the Fury of his Enemies.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Commanders from the Army arriv'd, and <hi>Mutaferaka,</hi> the chief of 'em, an intimate friend of <hi>Siaous</hi>'s, after he had pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately conferr'd with <hi>Soliman</hi> hautily demanded an Audience, which the Sultan would fain have refus'd him.</p>
            <p>He declar'd, that the Souldiers, having found that the Viſir <hi>Soliman</hi> was not able to command 'em, would no longer obey him, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him Head, and the Heads of the <hi>Kay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makan Redgeb,</hi> the Grand <hi>Teftarder,</hi> the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> with the heads of ſeveral Others, of which he deliver'd a Liſt in writing: That while they receiv'd his Highneſſes Orders they had made choice of <hi>Siaous</hi> for their Captain, a perſon of accompliſh'd Experience, and Zeal for the good of the Empire; that they hop'd the Sultan would approve their Choice, and would ſend him the Enſigns of an Employment which he merited by his Services and his Fidelity.</p>
            <p>But this Inſolence of the Army which went about to give Laws to their Soveraign, ſhook not <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Reſolutions as yet, for he thought by diſtributing Money among the Souldiers to appeaſe their fury; and they who either ſhar'd in his growing Troubles, or fear'd the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the mutiny, readily contributed to
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:95750:65"/>the raiſing a conſiderable Summ. The Sultaneſs <hi>Aſſeki</hi> gave two Thouſand Purſes, of five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Crowns each; the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi</hi> furniſh'd almoſt as much, and others proportionably: But the minds of the Souldiers were too much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated; they took the Money indeed, but it was all thrown away to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Mutiny therefore growing more outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and <hi>Siaous</hi> and <hi>Yeghen</hi> being Maſters of the Army, and in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where <hi>Soliman</hi> caus'd the Directors of the <hi>Moſquees</hi> to act their Parts, and the Sultan remaining Obſtinate, and reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather to loſe all, then deliver up the Viſir to the <hi>Mercy</hi> of his Enemies, bethought himſelf of taking another Courſe; which was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade the Viſir and the <hi>Caimacan,</hi> and to conferr the Employment of the firſt upon <hi>Siaous,</hi> and upon <hi>Cuproli</hi> his Brother in Law the place which the latter held; imagining that the Ambition of the Ringleaders being ſatisfy'd, the tumults would ceaſe.</p>
            <p>With theſe hopes, he ſent for <hi>Cuproli</hi> from the <hi>Dardanells,</hi> and made him <hi>Caimacan,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Redgeb,</hi> and diſpatch'd away the Seal of the Empire and <hi>Mahoment</hi>'s Standar'd to <hi>Siaous;</hi> but he declar'd he would never conſent to the death of Officers whom he eſteem'd both Loyal and faithful.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as <hi>Cuproli</hi> ſaw himſelf advanc'd to the ſecond place in the Empire, he had a private Conference with <hi>Soliman,</hi> and then it was that the Prince deſcover'd to him his deſign to make
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:95750:66"/>himſelf Maſter of the Empire, which till then he had always kept conceal'd in his Breaſt. Now in regard it was the Intereſt of this New <hi>Caima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> and <hi>Siaous,</hi> who found the power in their hands to attempt what they pleas'd, to corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond with the ambitious Deſigns of Prince <hi>Soliman,</hi> he found <hi>Cuproli</hi> inclin'd to ſecond his deſires, and undertook for <hi>Siaous,</hi> that he ſhould concurr with 'em in the Accompliſhment of their wiſhes.</p>
            <p>Things being in this Confuſion, and <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſtill reſolv'd not to abandon the Viſir to the Rage of the mutinous Souldiers, had caus'd him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon a ſafe Courſe, which was to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelf from the impetuoſity of their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, by retiring to the Prontiers of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and there to ſtay till Affairs might recover a new face, and furniſh him with a favourable Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to regain his Reputation.</p>
            <p>This was concluded between 'em, and ready to have been put in Execution: But the Viſir, who in the midſt of his Misfortunes could not forget his Deareſt <hi>Abra,</hi> deſir'd the <hi>Kiſler</hi> that he would engage himſelf to procure the delivery of but one more ſhort Letter to her, and afford that laſt comfort to a Friend whom perhaps he might never ſee again.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kiſler</hi> mov'd with compaſſion of his Friends overwhelming Misfortunes, would not refuſe him that laſt favour; ſo that being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the Letter, he gave it into the hands of an Eunuch, who was wont to carry others
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:95750:66"/>of the ſame nature to <hi>Sarai.</hi> But a moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Deſtiny, and unexpected accident hinder'd it from falling into the hands of that beloved Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident. For the Eunuch gave the Letter to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſlave, who ſeeing <hi>Sarai</hi> in the arms of Death, and believing there was ſome ſecret in the Gold Box, wherein the Letter was enclos'd, her cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity made her open it, and underſtanding by the reading of it, that the unknown perſon whom ſhe ſerv'd was that <hi>Abra,</hi> for whoſe loſs the Sultan was ſo extreamly troubled, ſhe thought the diſcovery of ſuch a ſecret would raiſe her Fortune, and therefore being introduc'd into <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s preſence, ſhe deliver'd the Box into his Hands; at what time the Sultan having o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd it, read the following words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Soliman</hi> Viſir to the Faithful <hi>Abra.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HEaven has overwhelm'd me with misfortunes; it only rais'd me to the higheſt Pinnacle of Honour to precipitate me thence. But, my dear <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> all my Afflictions would ſignifie little to me in compariſon of the loſs of your heart. If you continue faithful to the moſt unfortunate of Men, or if you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Sultan's Power, from whoſe Embraces I have ſo luckily wreſted yee, and to the troubleſom Paſſion of that other Rival, who as is reported, is labouring to purchaſe yee from the Sultaneſs, I ſhall look upon it as the Conſolation of all my Misfortunes. I am going a long journey, and I carry along with me, the dear
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:95750:67"/>Picture which you gave me. I kiſs it a thouſand times a day; and ſpeak to it what I cannot ſpeak to your ſelf. Love me, pitty me, and be aſſur'd, that the laſt ſigh of faithful <hi>Soliman</hi> will be for faithful <hi>Abra.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Never was ſurprize to be compar'd with that of the Sultan's; and never did ſo violent a Fury ſeize the heart of a Lover enrag'd, and a Maſter betray'd. He made a conſiderable preſent to the ſlave, and being exactly inform'd of every thing, and underſtanding that the Letter paſs'd through the <hi>Kiſler's</hi> hand, he bid her be ſilent, and ſo diſmiſt her.</p>
            <p>No ſooner was he alone by himſelf, but with a fuming Indignation ſparkling in his Eyes, and looking a ſecond time upon the Letter, the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſhall dye, cry'd he, with a ſigh of high diſpleaſure. How! a Favourite, upon whom I have heap'd my Favours, is it he that rends from my Boſom the Perſon whom I adore! An Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Eunuch, who my Bounty has rais'd from the Chains of Thraldom to exceſſive Power and Wealth betrays me in my own <hi>Serraglio,</hi> and in concert together both the one and the other make me their ſport, while I hazard the loſs of my Diadem to protect 'em from the fury of their Enemies. 'Tis too hard on my ſide, but they ſhall periſh both.</p>
            <p>Afterwards he rack'd his Brains, to penetrate who might be his other Rival. He knew the Sultaneſs could eaſily reſolve him, but he was loath to mention the matter to her. But at length
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:95750:67"/>after the firſt commotions of his Fury were over, he gave Orders to ſeize the Viſir, the <hi>Kiſler A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſi,</hi> and all the reſt whom the Soldiers demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as Victims to the tranquility of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
            <p>He order'd <hi>Abra</hi>'s Picture to be brought him, which was found about the Viſir in a little Caſe, and which he wore upon his heart; the ſight of the Picture redoubled his inward Vexations, and the fire of his Anger or'e ruling his Friendſhip which he thought abus'd by the fouleſt of all acts, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, he reſolv'd the Viſirs Ruin. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he was willing that the victim which he offer'd to his Love, ſhould be lookt upon as an oblation ſacrific'd to the publick good. To which purpoſe calling a <hi>Divan,</hi> wherein the new <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macan Cuproli</hi> preſided, he decreed the Death of the Viſir, the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> and of all the reſt whoſe Heads the Soldiers demanded, who under <hi>Yeghen,</hi> follow'd by <hi>Siaous,</hi> were marching with all ſpeed toward <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This decree was put in Execution the ſame day upon the Viſir; and the Sultan would needs have him tortur'd, to make him diſcover who was that other Lover mention'd in his Letter; but his generoſity would not permit him to make any Confeſſion: So that after he had ſuffer'd the Rack, he was ſtrangl'd in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> and his Head ſent to the Souldiers; and to give 'em entire ſatisfaction he order'd the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> the <hi>Caimacan Redgeb,</hi> the Grand <hi>Teftardar,</hi> and all the other unfortunate Objects of their Fury to
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:95750:68"/>be deliver'd up in Chains to their Fury, who no ſooner appear'd before the Army, but they were cut in pieces with a more then barbarous Inhumanity.</p>
            <p>The Army had already paſt through <hi>Adrianople,</hi> and were ſtill advancing, while the Sultan who thought he had fully ſatisfy'd 'em by this Bloody Sacrifice, was deſirous that his Love ſhould in ſome meaſure reap the Fruite of what he had done; to which purpoſe the New <hi>Agaſi</hi> took away <hi>Abra</hi> from the Sultaneſs, and ſhut her up again in the Serraglio of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> whither he went to Viſit her, ſhew'd her her Picture, together with the Viſir's laſt Letter, and upbraided her with all the ſevereſt Reproaches that ſhe could expect from an enraged Sultan, and a furious Lover.</p>
            <p>During this cruel <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> ſaw his ambitious Aims advancing toward their Accompliſhment. The Viſir, and all his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Friends, moſt Loyal to the Sultan, were now cut off. <hi>Siaous</hi> and <hi>Cuproli</hi> poſſeſs'd the two chiefeſt employments in the Empire, the Old <hi>Muſti</hi> was chang'd, and a new one put in by <hi>Cuproli,</hi> and the <hi>Imans</hi> ſtill heated the People, and ſupply'd 'em with fuel to feed the Flames of premeditated Revolt; but all this while he miſs'd the ſatisfaction of his Love, in regard the Sultan having broken all his private Meaſures with the Sultaneſs, had got <hi>Abra</hi> into his own Poſſeſſion; ſo that he ſaw no other way to wreſt her from his Embraces, but by aſcending his Throne, and making himſelf Lord of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio.</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:95750:68"/>
            <p>Every day brought ſome new Perſons over to his Party, and <hi>Cuproli,</hi> who by vertue of his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment preſided in the <hi>Divan,</hi> in the Viſir's Abſence had gain'd by his Artifices the new <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> whoſe Aſſiſtance was very neceſſary in caſe there ſhould be any Tumult in the Serraglio.</p>
            <p>The Prince therefore finding <hi>Abra</hi> forc'd away by the Sultan into a new Captivity, was affraid leaſt he ſhould make uſe of violence to procure the Satisfaction of his Love; and this it was which engag'd him to precipitate the Execution of his Deſign, for which he had all along taken his Meaſures with <hi>Cuproli,</hi> who was well convinc'd that <hi>Siaous</hi> and he enjoy'd their Employments only by vertue of that Force which had wreſted the Grant of 'em from the Sultan, and that they could not preſerve 'em but by placing <hi>Soliman</hi> upon the Throne.</p>
            <p>By this time the Army that ſtill march'd for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward under <hi>Yeghen,</hi> was not above two days March from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and <hi>Siaous</hi> follow'd with the Main Body, and the better to conceal his Deſign, faign'd a Quarrel with him, but their common Aim was the Depoſal of a Maſter whom they had offended, and who could never have a real Affection for 'em. As for <hi>Cuproli,</hi> he had made all the Proviſion that could be for the execution of the Enterprize, as well in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglios and his preparations of the <hi>Mufti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soliman</hi> therefore, for the ſake of his Amour, deſirous to haſten the Buſineſs, went to <hi>Cuproli,</hi> lay'd open to him the bottom of his Heart, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:95750:69"/>his Paſſion for <hi>Abra,</hi> and gave him moreover to underſtand, that in placing him upon the Throne they fulfill'd the Importunities of his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, but did nothing for the Repoſe of his Mind, which depended upon the Enjoyment of <hi>Abra,</hi> and preventing <hi>Mahomet's</hi> Paſſion from offering Vielence to her.</p>
            <p>She was in the Serraglio of Looking-Glaſſes deeply plung'd in ſorrow and Affliction, nor could ſhe reflect upon the unhappy Fate of her dear Viſir, ſtrangl'd by the order of his Rival, in whoſe power ſhe was, without aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning her ſelf to all that Rage and Deſpair could inſpire of moſt Diſmal and Mournful. She had ſeen her Picture in the Sultan's Hands, which he had not ſhew'd her, had it not been to tryumph the more barbarouſly over the Ruin of his Rival. By that, and by the Viſir's letter, ſhe knew that the Diſcovery of his Love was the only cauſe of his death and her Grief being ſo much the more bitter, by reaſon that death had depriv'd her of her dear Confident, nothing but only the Reſolution ſhe had taken to revenge herſelf upon <hi>Mahomet,</hi> had put a ſtop to the dire Effects of her own Deſpair.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the new <hi>Kiſler Agaſi</hi> having Engag'd himſelf in <hi>Soliman</hi>'s intereſts, and being inform'd of his Amours, offer'd himſelf to ſpeak to the <hi>Muſcovite</hi> in his behalf, and after he had diſcours'd her in private, he found her highly incens'd againſt <hi>Mahomet;</hi> and therefore to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite her the more willingly to correſpond with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limons</hi>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:95750:69"/>Paſſion, he thought it proper to impart to her the inclinations of the great Officers of the Empire, to ſet <hi>Soliman</hi> upon the Throne.</p>
            <p>Upon this Diſcovery, <hi>Abra</hi> who breath'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Revenge, put the <hi>Kiſler</hi> in ſome hopes, that ſo ſoon as Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> had ſatisfy'd her Revenge upon the Sultan's barbarous Cruelty, ſhe would be more enclin'd to favour his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kiſler</hi> gave Prince <hi>Soliman</hi> an account of this ſeeming Compliance; and that was enough to make him ſeek all ways to haſten that Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which he thought the only means to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at <hi>Abra</hi>'s Heart. In the mean time he deem'd it neceſſary to aſſure her, by a Billet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hand, that there was nothing which he would not willingly undertake, or endeavour to bring to paſs, ſo he might deſerve her Love.</p>
            <p>Now in regard that <hi>Mahomet</hi> had plac'd a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faithful Slave to attend upon <hi>Abra,</hi> that ſhe might have a watchful Eye upon all her Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, this Billet fell unhappily into the Sultan's Hands, who by that means found out who was that ſame formidable Rival whom the Viſir never would confeſs; ſo that he no ſooner had read it, but without any deliberation he determin'd a ſpeedy Revenge.</p>
            <p>'Twas Night, and therefore only attended with two of his Guards, he took his Arms, and flew to <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Appartiment with a furious Precipitancy, in hopes to ſacrifice him with his own hand to the attonement of his Rage.</p>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:95750:70"/>
            <p>Nor is there any queſtion but he had ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Project, had not <hi>Cuprilo</hi> and the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi,</hi> by taking true meaſures to prevent what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever might diſappoint their deſigns, and by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forth all neceſſary Orders to ſecure the life of him they lookt upon already as their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, fruſtrated the Effects of his Fury.</p>
            <p>The Eunuchs who guarded <hi>Soliman,</hi> defended the firſt door of his Appartiment, but <hi>Mahomet</hi> himſelf who fell upon 'em with more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary fury, after he had kill'd one and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded two more, had forc'd the firſt door, and without doubt had beat down the ſecond, had not the <hi>Kisler Agaſi</hi> haſten'd to the noiſe, with a Company of armed Eunuchs, who fell upon <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Guards, and conſtrain'd 'em to ſtand upon their own defence.</p>
            <p>The Sultan enrag'd to ſee the Agaſi in Arms againſt his Perſon, lay'd about him with his Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miter upon the Eunuchs, well ſeconded by his Guards, ſo that the Combat was beginning to be ſomewhat bloody, at what time the <hi>Boſtangi Bachi</hi> arriv'd with a good number of armed <hi>Boſtangi</hi>'s. <hi>Mahomet</hi> thinking he had been come to his aſſiſtance, order'd him to ſeize the Kiſler, and to put all the Eunuchs to the Sword; but the <hi>Boſtangi,</hi> who was one of <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, looking fiercely upon the Sultan, <hi>We no longer Acknowledge your Commands,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Your Life depends upon that Brother, who you are going baſely to Aſſaſſinate.</hi> The Sultan was ſo ſurpriz'd at theſe inſolent Words, that he ſtood like a Statue,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:95750:70"/>while his Guards betaking themſelves to flight, left him in the Power of the <hi>Boſtangi,</hi> who caus'd his Attendants to ſurround him, and after he had ſeiz'd and diſarm'd him, carry'd him to his Appartiment, where he was lockt up under a ſtrong Guard.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Kiſler</hi> carry'd the Princes into the old Serraglio, and <hi>Cuproli</hi> having aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl'd the <hi>Mufti,</hi> together with the Principal Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in <hi>Moſquee</hi> of <hi>Sta Sophia</hi> before day, there the <hi>Mahometan Pontiff</hi> ſign'd the <hi>Fetfa</hi> for the Depoſal of <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This firſt Ceremony being over, <hi>Cuproli</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair'd to the old Serraglio, caus'd <hi>Soliman</hi> to be plac'd upon a kind of a Throne, and having proclaim'd him Sultan, was the firſt himſelf that pay'd him Homage. After this, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd it to his pleaſure to diſpoſe of <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Deſtiny, who thought it ſufficient to ſhut him up during the Remainder of his days.</p>
            <p>His Ambition being thus ſatisfy'd, the only thing he apply'd his Mind to next, was to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his Love. To which purpoſe he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Kiſler Agaſi</hi> to repair with all ſpeed to <hi>Calcedon,</hi> and bring away the Sultaneſs <hi>Abra;</hi> whom he declar'd his <hi>Aſſeki,</hi> and to deliver her a Letter which he wrote to her in the following Termes.</p>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:95750:71"/>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sultan</hi> Soliman <hi>to the Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> Aſſeki, Abra-Mulè.</head>
                  <p>YOU are reveng'd, fair <hi>Abra, Mahomet</hi> is puniſh'd, and I am upon the Throne; the Only reaſon I attempted to aſcend it, was only to make you the Miſtreſs of my Empire, as you are of my heart. Come then and ſatisfy the Impatience of my Love, and enjoy all the Grandeurs you deſerve. Your Word is a ſufficient Pledge for the Pleaſures I expect from you, and for that which you ought to take, in being the Only Sultaneſs of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Sultan <hi>Soliman.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Abra</hi> joyfully receiv'd the news which the <hi>Kiſler</hi> brought her, that ſhe was reveng'd upon <hi>Mahomet;</hi> but in regard ſhe was not ignorant that the Viſir's Misfortunss had been the Effect of a Conſpiracy between <hi>Siaous, Cuproli,</hi> and <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and conſequently that the Prince was the real Author of his death, ſhe abhor'd him with the utmoſt Hatred that an Injur'd heart could be capable of.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:95750:71"/>
            <p>Therefore ſhe liſten'd very heedfully to the <hi>Kiſler,</hi> read <hi>Soliman</hi>'s Letter, and then fixing her Eyes upon the Eunuch, Never, ſaid ſhe, did Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Love a man with that Fervency and Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity as I lov'd the Viſir; for his ſake I diſdain'd and contemn'd all the Advantages wherewith <hi>Mahomet</hi> could flatter my Ambition; nor have I leſs deſpis'd Prince <hi>Soliman</hi>'s vehement Paſſion. <hi>Mahomet</hi> put to death my Lover and I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd, but the Diſaſter that befell that Lover was the Workman ſhip of Sultan <hi>Soliman</hi>'s ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices, and I have not a Heart ſo baſe and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous to ſeek my Revenge upon his perſon, by foul and ignominious means, with which a counterfeit Affection might furniſh me, ſo that not being able to puniſh him any other way, then by wreſting my ſelf from the Embraces of his Paſſion, you ſhall tell him how I correſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Love. And having pronounc'd theſe laſt words; ſhe drew forth a dagger which ſhe held conceal'd under her upper Garment, and ſtabbing herſelf through the heart fell dead at the <hi>Kiſler</hi>'s feet.</p>
            <p>Such was the diſmal Cataſtrophe of <hi>Abra-Mulè</hi>'s Amours; ſo fatal to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, and to three Unfortunate Lovers. The Viſir, whom ſhe lov'd, was ſtrangl'd; <hi>Mahomet</hi> loſt his Empire, and <hi>Soliman</hi> fell into ſuch a terrible fit of Melancholly and dozing Vexation, that he
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:95750:72"/>only languiſh'd upon the Throne in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and continual Penſiveneſs, the cauſe of which few perſons knew; and at length, falling into a kind of inſenſibility of every Thing, exceſs of inward Grief, that never left him, brought him to his end.</p>
            <trailer>The END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95750:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
